<root><template><title>other uses</title></template>
<template lineStart="1"><title>pp-semi</title><part><name>small</name><equals>=</equals><value>yes</value></part></template>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Infobox person
</title><part><name> name </name><equals>=</equals><value> Terry Fox
</value></part><part><name> image </name><equals>=</equals><value> TerryFoxToronto19800712.JPG
</value></part><part><name> imagesize </name><equals>=</equals><value> 200px
</value></part><part><name> alt </name><equals>=</equals><value> A young man with short, curly hair and an artificial right leg runs down a street. He wears shorts and a T-shirt that reads &quot;Marathon of Hope&quot;
</value></part><part><name> caption </name><equals>=</equals><value> Terry Fox in Toronto during his Marathon of Hope cross-country run (July 1980)
</value></part><part><name> birth_date </name><equals>=</equals><value> <template><title>birth date</title><part><name>mf</name><equals>=</equals><value>yes</value></part><part><name index="1"/><value>1958</value></part><part><name index="2"/><value>7</value></part><part><name index="3"/><value>28</value></part></template>
</value></part><part><name> birth_place </name><equals>=</equals><value> [[Winnipeg]], [[Manitoba]], Canada
</value></part><part><name> birth_name </name><equals>=</equals><value> Terrance Stanley Fox
</value></part><part><name> death_date </name><equals>=</equals><value> <template><title>death date and age</title><part><name>mf</name><equals>=</equals><value>yes</value></part><part><name index="1"/><value>1981</value></part><part><name index="2"/><value>6</value></part><part><name index="3"/><value>28</value></part><part><name index="4"/><value>1958</value></part><part><name index="5"/><value>7</value></part><part><name index="6"/><value>28</value></part></template>
</value></part><part><name> death_place </name><equals>=</equals><value> [[New Westminster]], [[British Columbia]], Canada
</value></part><part><name> death_cause </name><equals>=</equals><value> [[Metastasis|Metastatic]] [[osteosarcoma]]
</value></part><part><name> known_for </name><equals>=</equals><value> Marathon of Hope
</value></part><part><name> education </name><equals>=</equals><value> [[Simon Fraser University]]
</value></part><part><name> title </name><equals>=</equals><value> Companion of the [[Order of Canada]]
</value></part></template>

'''Terrance Stanley &quot;Terry&quot; Fox''' <template><title>Post-nominals</title><part><name>post-noms</name><equals>=</equals><value>[[Order of Canada|CC]] [[Order of the Dogwood|OD]]</value></part></template>, (July 28, 1958 – June 28, 1981) was a [[Canadians|Canadian]] [[Humanitarianism|humanitarian]], athlete, and [[cancer research]] activist. In 1980, with one leg having been amputated, he embarked on a cross-Canada run to raise money and awareness for cancer research. Although the spread of his cancer eventually forced him to end his quest after 143 days and <template><title>convert</title><part><name index="1"/><value>5373</value></part><part><name index="2"/><value>km</value></part><part><name index="3"/><value>mi</value></part></template>, and ultimately cost him his life, his efforts resulted in a lasting, worldwide legacy. The annual [[Terry Fox Run]], first held in 1981, has grown to involve millions of participants in over 60 countries and is now the world's largest one-day fundraiser for cancer research; over [[Canadian dollar|C$]]500 million has been raised in his name.

Fox was a distance runner and [[basketball]] player for his [[Port Coquitlam]], [[British Columbia]], high school and [[Simon Fraser University]]. His right leg was amputated in 1977 after he was diagnosed with [[osteosarcoma]], though he continued to run using an artificial leg. He also played [[wheelchair basketball]] in [[Vancouver]], winning three national championships.

In 1980, he began the Marathon of Hope, a cross-country run to raise money for cancer research. Fox hoped to raise one dollar for each of Canada's 24 million people. He began with little fanfare from [[St John's, Newfoundland and Labrador|St. John's]], [[Newfoundland and Labrador|Newfoundland]], in April and ran the equivalent of a full [[marathon]] every day. Fox had become a national star by the time he reached [[Ontario]]; he made numerous public appearances with businessmen, athletes, and politicians in his efforts to raise money. He was forced to end his run outside of [[Thunder Bay]] when the cancer spread to his lungs. His hopes of overcoming the disease and completing his marathon ended when he died nine months later.

Fox was the youngest person ever named a Companion of the [[Order of Canada]]. He won the 1980 [[Lou Marsh Award]] as the nation's top sportsman and was named [[Canadian Newsmaker of the Year|Canada's Newsmaker of the Year]] in both 1980 and 1981. Considered a national hero, he has had many buildings, roads and parks named in his honour across the country.

<h level="2" i="1">==Early life and cancer==</h>
Terry Fox was born on July 28, 1958, in [[Winnipeg]], [[Manitoba]], to Rolland &quot;Rolly&quot; Fox and [[Betty Fox]]. Rolly was a switchman for the [[Canadian National Railway]].<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;MtlGazette42880&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite news |last=Scrivener |first=Leslie |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=kBQyAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=aaQFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=1162,4206618 |title=Terry's running for the cancer society |newspaper=Montreal Gazette |date=1980-04-28 |accessdate=2010-02-25 |page=21}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Terry had an elder brother, Fred, a younger brother, Darrell and a younger sister, Judith.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Greatest Canadian&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite news |url=http://www.cbc.ca/greatest/top_ten/nominee/fox-terry.html |title=The Greatest Canadian: Terry Fox |publisher=Canadian Broadcasting Corporation |accessdate=2010-02-25| archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080704121456/http://www.cbc.ca/greatest/top_ten/nominee/fox-terry.html| archivedate = July 4, 2008}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> His family moved to [[Surrey, British Columbia|Surrey]], [[British Columbia]], in 1966, then settled in [[Port Coquitlam, British Columbia|Port Coquitlam]] in 1968.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Greatest Canadian&quot; </attr></ext> His parents were dedicated to their family, and his mother was especially protective of her children; it was through her that Fox developed his stubborn dedication to whatever task he committed to do.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Scrivener13&quot;</attr><inner>Scrivener, 2000, pp. 13–14.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> His father recalled that he was extremely competitive, noting that Terry hated to lose so much that he would continue at any activity until he succeeded.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Inwood&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite news |first=Damian |last=Inwood |title=Terry Fox: 25 years; Celebrating his dream: a 12-page special section honouring the 25th Annual Terry Fox Run |newspaper=Vancouver Province |date=2005-09-18}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

He was an enthusiastic athlete, playing [[soccer]], [[Rugby football|rugby]] and [[baseball]] as a child.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Scrivener16&quot;</attr><inner>Scrivener, 2000, pp. 16–17.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> His passion was for [[basketball]] and though he stood only five feet tall and was a poor player at the time, Fox sought to make his school team in grade eight. His physical education teacher and basketball coach at Mary Hill Junior High School felt he was better suited to be a distance runner and encouraged him to take up the sport. Fox had no desire for cross-country running, but took it up because he respected and wanted to please his coach.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Scrivener, 2000, p. 18.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> He was determined to continue playing basketball, even if he was the last substitute on the team. Fox played only one minute in his grade eight season but dedicated his summers to improving his play. He became a regular player in grade nine and earned a starting position in grade ten.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Scrivener, 2000, pp. 19–20.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> In grade 12, he won his high school's athlete of the year award jointly with his best friend Doug Alward.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Greatest Canadian&quot; </attr></ext>

Though he was initially unsure if he wanted to go to university, Fox's mother convinced him to enrol at [[Simon Fraser University]], where he studied [[kinesiology]] as a stepping stone to becoming a physical education teacher.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Scrivener, 2000, p. 23.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> He tried out for the junior varsity basketball team, earning a spot ahead of more talented players due to his determination.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Greatest Canadian&quot; </attr></ext>

On November 12, 1976, as Fox was driving home to Port Coquitlam, he became distracted by nearby bridge construction, and crashed into the back of a pickup truck. While his car was left undriveable, Fox emerged with only a sore right knee. He again felt pain in December, but chose to ignore it until the end of basketball season.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Scrivener, 2000, p. 25.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> By March 1977, the pain had intensified and he finally went to a hospital, where he was diagnosed with [[osteosarcoma]], a form of cancer that often starts near the knees.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Greatest Canadian&quot; </attr></ext> Fox believed his car accident weakened his knee and left it vulnerable to the disease, though his doctors argued there was no connection.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Scrivener, 2000, p. 27.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> He was told that his leg had to be amputated, he would require [[chemotherapy]] treatment, and that recent medical advances meant he had a 50 percent chance of survival. Fox learned that two years before the figure would have been only 15 percent; the improvement in survival rates impressed on him the value of cancer research.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Scrivener, 2000, p. 30.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

With the help of an artificial leg, Fox was walking three weeks after the amputation.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Greatest Canadian&quot; </attr></ext> He then progressed to playing golf with his father.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Scrivener, 2000, p. 36.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Doctors were impressed with Fox's positive outlook, stating it contributed to his rapid recovery.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Scrivener, 2000, p. 35.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> He endured sixteen months of chemotherapy and found the time he spent in the British Columbia Cancer Control Agency facility difficult as he watched fellow cancer patients suffer and die from the disease.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Scrivener, 2000, pp. 37–38.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Fox ended his treatment with new purpose: he felt he owed his survival to medical advances and wished to live his life in a way that would help others find courage.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Scrivener, 2000, p. 41.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

In the summer of 1977 [[Rick Hansen]], working with the Canadian Wheelchair Sports Association, invited Fox to try out for his [[wheelchair basketball]] team.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |last=Edwards |first=Peter |title=Man in Motion set to honour pal Terry Fox |newspaper=Toronto Star |date=1987-01-03 |page=A13}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Although he was undergoing chemotherapy treatments at the time, Fox's energy impressed Hansen.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Greatest Canadian&quot; </attr></ext> Less than two months after learning how to play the sport, Fox was named a member of the team for the national championship in Edmonton.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Scrivener, 2000, p. 45.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> He won three national titles with the team,<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Greatest Canadian&quot; </attr></ext> and was named an all-star by the North American Wheelchair Basketball Association in 1980.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Scrivener, 2000, p. 47.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

<h level="2" i="2">==Marathon of Hope==</h>
[[File:Terry Fox Denkmal.jpg|thumb|right|Terry Fox statue in [[Beacon Hill Park]], Victoria, British Columbia|alt= Statue of Fox running set on a plinth engraved with &quot;Somewhere the hurting must stop...&quot; ]]
The night before his cancer surgery, Fox had been given an article about [[Dick Traum]], the first amputee to complete the [[New York City Marathon]].<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Greatest Canadian&quot; </attr></ext> The article inspired him; he embarked on a 14-month training program, telling his family he planned to compete in a marathon himself.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;MtlGazette42880&quot; </attr></ext> In private, he devised a more extensive plan. His hospital experiences had made Fox angry at how little money was dedicated to cancer research. He intended to run the length of Canada in the hope of increasing cancer awareness, a goal he initially only divulged to his friend Douglas Alward.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Scrivener, 2000, p. 58.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

Fox ran with an unusual gait, as he was required to hop-step on his good leg due to the extra time the springs in his artificial leg required to reset after each step.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;MtlGazette62380&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite news |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=2FQ0AAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=abkFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=3901,1065955 |title=Runner wants to cross nation on one leg |newspaper=Montreal Gazette |date=1980-06-23 |accessdate=2010-02-26 |page=1}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> He found the training painful as the additional pressure he had to place on both his good leg and his stump led to bone bruises, blisters and intense pain. Fox found that after about 20&amp;nbsp;minutes of each run, he crossed a pain threshold and the run became easier.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Scrivener, 2000, p. 57.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

In August 1979, Fox competed in a marathon in [[Prince George, British Columbia]]. He finished in last place, ten minutes behind his closest competitor, but his effort was met with tears and applause from the other participants.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Greatest Canadian&quot; </attr></ext> Following the marathon, he revealed his full plan to his family.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Coupland, 2005, p. 29.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> His mother discouraged him, angering Fox, though she later came to support the project. She recalled, &quot;He said, 'I thought you'd be one of the first persons to believe in me.' And I wasn't. I was the first person who let him down&quot;.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=maclean</attr></ext> Fox initially hoped to raise $1&amp;nbsp;million,<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;maclean&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite news |last=MacQueen |first=Ken |url=http://www.canadianencyclopedia.ca/index.cfm?PgNm=TCE&amp;Params=M1ARTM0012749 |title=25th anniversary of Terry Fox's Marathon of Hope |newspaper=Macleans Magazine |publisher=Historica-Dominion Institute of Canada |date=2005-04-04 |accessdate=2010-03-20}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> then $10 million, but later sought to raise $1 for each of Canada's 24 million people.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;CBCLegacy&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite news |url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/background/fox_terry/ |title=Terry Fox's legacy of hope |publisher=Canadian Broadcasting Corporation |date=2006-06-27 |accessdate=2010-02-25}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

<h level="3" i="3">===Preparation===</h>
On October 15, 1979, Fox sent a letter to the [[Canadian Cancer Society]] in which he announced his goal and appealed for funding. He stated that he would &quot;conquer&quot; his disability, and promised to complete his run, even if he had to &quot;crawl every last mile&quot;. Explaining why he wanted to raise money for research, Fox described his personal experience of cancer treatment:

<template lineStart="1"><title>quote</title><part><name index="1"/><value>I soon realized that that would only be half my quest, for as I went through the 16 months of the physically and emotionally draining ordeal of chemotherapy, I was rudely awakened by the feelings that surrounded and coursed through the cancer clinic. There were faces with the brave smiles, and the ones who had given up smiling. There were feelings of hopeful denial, and the feelings of despair. My quest would not be a selfish one. I could not leave knowing these faces and feelings would still exist, even though I would be set free from mine. Somewhere the hurting must stop....and I was determined to take myself to the limit for this cause.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;cosentino&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite book| author = Cosentino, Frank| title = Not bad, eh?: great moments in Canadian sports history| url = http://books.google.com/?id=5AagweEwvVgC| year = 1990| publisher = General Store Publishing House| isbn = 978-0-919431-29-4| pages = 63–64 }}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext></value></part></template>

Fox made no promises that his efforts would lead to a cure for cancer, but he closed his letter with the statement: &quot;We need your help. The people in cancer clinics all over the world need people who believe in miracles. I am not a dreamer, and I am not saying that this will initiate any kind of definitive answer or cure to cancer. I believe in miracles. I have to.&quot;<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=cosentino</attr></ext> The Cancer Society was skeptical of his dedication, but agreed to support Fox once he had acquired sponsors and requested he get a medical certificate from a heart specialist stating that he was fit to attempt the run. Fox was diagnosed with [[left ventricular hypertrophy]] — an enlarged heart — a condition commonly associated with athletes. Doctors warned Fox of the potential risks he faced, though they did not consider his condition a significant concern. They endorsed his participation when he promised that he would stop immediately if he began to experience any heart problems.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Scrivener, 2000, pp. 69–70.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

A second letter was sent to several corporations seeking donations for a vehicle, running shoes and to cover the other costs of the run.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Scrivener63&quot;</attr><inner>Scrivener, 2000, p. 63.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Fox sent other letters asking for grants to buy a running leg. He observed that while he was grateful to be alive following his cancer treatment, &quot;I remember promising myself that, should I live, I would rise up to meet this new challenge [of fundraising for cancer research] face to face and prove myself worthy of life, something too many people take for granted.&quot;<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Scrivener63&quot; </attr></ext> The [[Ford Motor Company]] donated a camper van,<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Scrivener13&quot; </attr></ext> while [[Imperial Oil]] contributed fuel, and [[Adidas]] his running shoes.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Murphy33&quot;</attr><inner>Murphy, 2005, p. 33.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Fox turned away any company that requested he endorse their products and refused any donation that carried conditions as he insisted that nobody was to profit from his run.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Scrivener13&quot; </attr></ext>

<h level="3" i="4">===Trek across Canada===</h>
[[File:Marathon of Hope path.png|thumb|right|Fox's path across eastern Canada. He began at St. John's on the east coast and ran west.|alt= refer to caption]]
The Marathon began on April 12, 1980, when Fox dipped his right leg in the Atlantic Ocean near [[St John's, Newfoundland and Labrador|St. John's]], [[Newfoundland and Labrador|Newfoundland]], and filled two large bottles with ocean water. He intended to keep one as a souvenir and pour the other into the Pacific Ocean upon completing his journey at [[Victoria, British Columbia]].<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;CBCLegacy&quot; </attr></ext> Fox was supported on his run by Doug Alward, who drove the van and cooked meals.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Murphy33&quot; </attr></ext>

Fox was met with gale force winds, heavy rain and a snowstorm in the first days of his run.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;MtlGazette42880&quot; </attr></ext> He was initially disappointed with the reception he received, but was heartened upon arriving in [[Channel-Port aux Basques, Newfoundland and Labrador|Port aux Basques, Newfoundland]], where the town's 10,000 residents presented him with a donation of over $10,000.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Murphy33&quot; </attr></ext> Throughout the trip, Fox frequently expressed his anger and frustration to those he saw as impeding the run, and he fought regularly with Alward. By the time they reached [[Nova Scotia]], they were barely on speaking terms, and it was arranged for Fox's brother Darrell, then 17, to join them as a buffer.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=maclean</attr></ext> Fox left the [[Maritimes]] on June 10 and faced new challenges entering [[Quebec]] due to his group's inability to speak [[French language|French]]<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Scrivener232&quot;</attr><inner>Scrivener, 2000, p. 232.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> and drivers who continually forced him off the road.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Scrivener, 2000, p. 97&quot;</attr><inner>Scrivener, 2000, p. 97.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Fox arrived in [[Montreal]] on June 22, one-third of the way through his <template><title>convert</title><part><name index="1"/><value>8000</value></part><part><name index="2"/><value>km</value></part><part><name index="3"/><value>mi</value></part><part><name>adj</name><equals>=</equals><value>on</value></part></template> journey, having collected over $200,000 in donations.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;MtlGazette62380&quot; </attr></ext> Around this time, Terry Fox's run caught the attention of [[Isadore Sharp]] who was the founder and CEO of Four Seasons Hotel and Resorts—and who had lost a son to melanoma in 1978 just a year after Terry's diagnosis.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Sandra Martin, [http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/national/betty-fox-kept-marathon-of-hope-pure-and-terry-foxs-legacy-alive/article2066430/page3/ Obituary]: Betty Fox kept Marathon of Hope pure and Terry Fox’s legacy alive, [[The Globe and Mail]], Friday June 17, 2011</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Sharp was intrigued by the story of a one-legged kid &quot;trying to do the impossible&quot; and run across the country; so he offered food and accommodation at his hotels en route. When Terry was discouraged because so few people were making donations, Sharp pledged $2 a mile [to the run] and persuaded close to 1,000 other corporations to do the same.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Martin, Obituary: Betty Fox kept Marathon of Hope Pure..., [[The Globe and Mail]], Friday June 17, 2011</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Sharp's encouragement persuaded Terry to continue with the Marathon of Hope. Convinced by the Canadian Cancer Society that arriving in [[Ottawa]] for [[Canada Day]] would aid fundraising efforts, he remained in Montreal for a few extra days.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Scrivener, 2000, p. 97&quot;</attr></ext>

[[File:Terry Fox memorial, St. John's.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Memorial at Mile 0 in [[St John's, Newfoundland and Labrador|St. John's]]]]
Fox crossed into Ontario at the town of [[Hawkesbury, Ontario|Hawkesbury]] on the last Saturday in June. He was met by a brass band and thousands of residents who lined the streets to cheer him on, while the [[Ontario Provincial Police]] gave him an escort throughout the province.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Murphy34&quot;</attr><inner>Murphy, 2005, p. 34.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Despite the sweltering heat of summer, he continued to run <template><title>convert</title><part><name index="1"/><value>26</value></part><part><name index="2"/><value>mi</value></part><part><name index="3"/><value>km</value></part></template> per day.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Scrivener232&quot; </attr></ext> On his arrival in [[Ottawa]], Fox met [[Governor General of Canada|Governor General]] [[Edward Schreyer|Ed Schreyer]] and [[Prime Minister of Canada|Prime Minister]] [[Pierre Trudeau]] and was the guest of honour at numerous sporting events in the city.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Murphy34&quot; </attr></ext> In front of 16,000 fans, he performed a ceremonial kickoff at a [[Canadian Football League]] game and was given a standing ovation. Fox's journal reflected his growing excitement at the reception he had received as he began to understand how deeply moved Canadians were by his efforts.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Scrivener, 2000, p. 118.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

A crowd of 10,000 people met Fox in [[Toronto]], where he was honoured in [[Nathan Phillips Square]]. As he ran to the square, he was joined on the road by many people, including [[National Hockey League]] star [[Darryl Sittler]], who presented Fox with his 1980 All-Star Game jersey. The Cancer Society estimated it collected $100,000 in donations that day alone.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Greatest Canadian&quot; </attr></ext> As he continued through southern Ontario, he was met by [[Hockey Hall of Fame]]r [[Bobby Orr]] who presented him with a cheque for $25,000. Fox considered meeting Orr the highlight of his journey.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Greatest Canadian&quot; </attr></ext>

<template lineStart="1"><title>Quote box </title><part><name>quote </name><equals>=</equals><value>&quot;Everybody seems to have given up hope of trying. I haven't. It isn't easy and it isn't supposed to be, but I'm accomplishing something. How many people give up a lot to do something good. I'm sure we would have found a cure for cancer 20 years ago if we had really tried&quot;</value></part><part><name>align</name><equals>=</equals><value>left </value></part><part><name>width</name><equals>=</equals><value>30%</value></part><part><name>source</name><equals>=</equals><value>Fox speaking outside of Ottawa<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=Inwood</attr></ext></value></part></template>
As Fox's fame grew, the Cancer Society scheduled him to attend more functions and give more speeches.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Scrivener, 2000, p. 123.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Fox attempted to accommodate any request that he believed would raise money, no matter how far out of his way it took him.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Coupland, 2005, p. 91.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> He bristled, however, at what he felt were media intrusions into his personal life, for example when the ''[[Toronto Star]]'' reported that he had gone on a date.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Scrivener, 2000, p. 130.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Fox was left unsure whom he could trust in the media after negative articles began to emerge, including one by the ''[[Globe and Mail]]'' that characterized him as a &quot;tyrannical brother&quot; who verbally abused Darrell and claimed he was running because he held a grudge against a doctor who had misdiagnosed his condition, allegations he referred to as &quot;trash&quot;.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Scrivener144&quot; </attr></ext>

The physical demands of running a marathon every day took its toll on Fox's body. Apart from the rest days in Montreal taken at the request of the Cancer Society, he refused to take a day off, even on his 22nd birthday.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Scrivener, 2000, p. 138.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> He frequently suffered shin splints and an inflamed knee. He developed cysts on his stump and experienced dizzy spells.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Coupland, 2005, p. 47.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> At one point, he suffered a soreness in his ankle that would not go away. Although he feared he had developed a stress fracture, he ran for three more days before seeking medical attention, and was then relieved to learn it was [[tendonitis]] and could be treated with painkillers.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Scrivener, 2000, p. 147.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Fox rejected calls for him to seek regular medical checkups,<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |last=Harper |first=Tim |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=EaMyAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=ie4FAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=980,3731630 |title=Medical check 'stupid', cancer marathoner scoffs |newspaper=Ottawa Citizen |date=1980-07-30 |accessdate=2010-02-28 |page=1}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> and dismissed suggestions he was risking his future health.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Scrivener144&quot;</attr><inner>Scrivener, 2000, p. 144.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

In spite of his immense recuperative capacity,<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Scrivener, 2000, p. 133.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Fox found that by late August he was exhausted before he began his day's run.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Scrivener, 2000, p. 150.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> On September 1, outside of Thunder Bay, he was forced to stop briefly after he suffered an intense coughing fit and experienced pains in his chest. Unsure what to do, he resumed running as the crowds along the highway shouted out their encouragement.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Scrivener, 2000, pp. 153–154.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> A few miles later, short of breath and with continued chest pain, he asked Alward to drive him to a hospital. He feared immediately that he had run his last kilometer.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Scrivener, 2000, p. 155.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> The next day, Fox held a tearful press conference during which he announced that his cancer had returned and spread to his lungs. He was forced to end his run after 143 days and <template><title>convert</title><part><name index="1"/><value>5373</value></part><part><name index="2"/><value>km</value></part><part><name index="3"/><value>mi</value></part></template>.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/background/fox_terry/ |title=Terry Fox's legacy of hope |newspaper=CBC News Online |date=2006-06-27 |accessdate=2010-06-16 |page=1}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Fox refused offers to complete the run in his stead, stating that he wanted to complete his marathon himself.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Greatest Canadian&quot; </attr></ext>

<h level="3" i="5">===National response===</h>
[[File:Terry Fox Statue db.jpg|right|thumb|Terry Fox statue in [[Ottawa]]|alt=Statue of a runner with an artificial leg partially hunched forward.]]
Fox had raised $1.7 million by the time he was forced to abandon the Marathon. He realized that the nation was about to see the consequences of the disease, and hoped that this might lead to greater generosity.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Scrivener, 2000, p. 163.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> A week after his run ended, the [[CTV Television Network]] organized a nationwide [[telethon]] in support of Fox and the Canadian Cancer Society.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=vTMyAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=qaQFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=2345%2C3013106 |title=TV show raises $9 million for cancer |newspaper=Montreal Gazette |date=1980-09-08 |page=1 |accessdate=2010-02-28}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Supported by Canadian and international celebrities, the five-hour event raised $10.5 million.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Greatest Canadian&quot; </attr></ext> Among the donations were $1 million each by the governments of British Columbia and Ontario, the former to create a new research institute to be founded in Fox's name, and the latter an endowment given to the Ontario Cancer Treatment and Research Foundation.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Scrivener, 2000, p. 168.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Donations continued throughout the winter, and by the following April, over $23 million had been raised.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=-CMiAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=-IcFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=1251,3421230 |title=Fox's dream raised $23.4 million |newspaper=Tri-City Herald |date=1981-04-12 |accessdate=2010-02-28 |page=44}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

Supporters and well wishers from around the world inundated Fox with letters and tokens of support. At one point, he was receiving more mail than the rest of Port Coquitlam combined.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=a9AyAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=ZO4FAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5134,2930871 |title=Terry Fox receives mountains of mail |newspaper=Ottawa Citizen |date=1980-12-24 |accessdate=2010-02-28 |page=8}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Such was his fame that one letter addressed simply to &quot;Terry Fox, Canada&quot; was successfully delivered.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1338&amp;dat=19801226&amp;id=zwZMAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=Q_kDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=6280,3430076|title=Fan mail: To 'Terry Fox, Canada' |newspaper=Spokane Daily Chronicle |date=1980-12-26 |accessdate=2010-02-28 |page=6}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

In September 1980 he was invested in a special ceremony as a Companion of the [[Order of Canada]]; he was the youngest person to be so honoured.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{Cite news
|url= http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=i7MSAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=QvkDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=3462,5760689&amp;dq=terry+fox+order+of+canada+highest+civilian&amp;hl=en
|title=Canada Honors One-legged Cancer Runner |newspaper= Spokane Daily Chronicle|date= September 20, 1980
|accessdate=20 September 2010
}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext><ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=eZckAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=raQFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=1331,3019823 |title=Terry Fox to get Order of Canada |newspaper=Montreal Gazette |date=1980-09-16 |accessdate=2010-02-28 |page=1}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> The [[Lieutenant Governor of British Columbia]] named him to the [[Order of the Dogwood]], the province's highest award.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=1VsxAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=p6QFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4605,3592810 |title=B. C. will give award to native son Terry Fox |newspaper=Montreal Gazette |date=1980-10-18 |accessdate=2010-02-28 |page=28}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> [[Canada's Sports Hall of Fame]] commissioned a permanent exhibit,<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=BvQjAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=WO4DAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4464,3383307 |title=Runner gets award |newspaper=Spokane Spokesman-Review |date=1981-02-08 |accessdate=2010-02-28 |page=B4}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> and Fox was named the winner of the [[Lou Marsh Award]] for 1980 as the nation's top athlete.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=OAciAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=u6QFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4842,3290988 |title=Courageous Terry Fox captures Lou Marsh Award |newspaper=Montreal Gazette |date=1980-12-18 |accessdate=2010-02-28 |page=57}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> He was named Canada's 1980 [[Canadian Newsmaker of the Year|Newsmaker of the Year]]. The ''[[Ottawa Citizen]]'' described the national response to his marathon as &quot;one of the most powerful outpourings of emotion and generosity in Canada's history&quot;.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |last=MacQueen |first=Ken |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=bdAyAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=ZO4FAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=6826,207028 |title=Terry Fox: His run taught Canadians to hope |newspaper=Ottawa Citizen |date=1980-12-29 |accessdate=2010-02-28 |page=42}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

<h level="2" i="6">==Death==</h>
In the following months, Fox received multiple chemotherapy treatments; however, the disease continued to spread.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=lgUiAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=xKQFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=6092,3261447 |title=Fox's cancer spreads |newspaper=Montreal Gazette |date=1981-01-29 |accessdate=2010-02-28 |page=1}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> As his condition worsened, Canadians hoped for a miracle and [[Pope John Paul II]] sent a telegram saying that he was praying for Fox.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=9OchAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=82cEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=6555,3616902 |title=Pope prays for cancer victim |newspaper=Sarasota Herald-Tribune |date=1981-03-07 |accessdate=2010-02-28 |page=8A}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Doctors turned to experimental [[interferon]] treatments, though their effectiveness against osteogenic sarcoma was unknown.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Scrivener, 2000, p. 176.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> He suffered an adverse reaction to his first treatment,<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=V-4yAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=V-4FAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5396,3500932 |title=Guard patrols Terry's room |newspaper=Ottawa Citizen |date=1981-02-23 |accessdate=2010-02-28 |page=8}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> but continued the program after a period of rest.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=f6MyAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=3u4FAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4330,586883 |title=Fox 'not doing too well,' feeling more pain: doctor |newspaper=Ottawa Citizen |date=1981-06-23 |accessdate=2010-02-28 |page=8}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

Fox was re-admitted to the [[Royal Columbian Hospital]] in [[New Westminster]] on June 19, 1981, with chest congestion and developed [[pneumonia]].<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=OocfAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=FdIEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=2649,5580957 |title=Fox's condition worsens |newspaper=Daytona Beach Morning Journal |date=1981-06-23 |accessdate=2010-02-28 |page=8B}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> He fell into a [[coma]] and died at 4:35&amp;nbsp;a.m. [[Pacific Daylight Time|PDT]] on June 28, 1981, with his family by his side.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=hKMyAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=3u4FAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=1468%2C4697989 |title=Terry Fox dies |newspaper=Ottawa Citizen |date=1981-06-29 |accessdate=2010-02-28 |page=1}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext><ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>[http://archives.cbc.ca/on_this_day/06/28/ CBC Archive Film]</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> The Government of Canada ordered flags across the country lowered to half staff, an unprecedented honour that was usually reserved for statesmen.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=L-gLAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=clkDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=7145,4492919 |title=Fox succumbs to cancer |newspaper=St. Petersburg Evening Independent |date=1981-06-29 |accessdate=2010-02-28 |page=2C}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Addressing the [[House of Commons of Canada|House of Commons]], Trudeau said, &quot;It occurs very rarely in the life of a nation that the courageous spirit of one person unites all people in the celebration of his life and in the mourning of his death ... We do not think of him as one who was defeated by misfortune but as one who inspired us with the example of the triumph of the human spirit over adversity&quot;.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Scrivener182&quot;</attr><inner>Scrivener, 2000, p. 182.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

His funeral, attended by 40 relatives and 200 guests,<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Scrivener182&quot; </attr></ext> was broadcast on national television; hundreds of communities across Canada also held memorial services,<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1981/07/03/world/around-the-world-canada-televises-funeral-of-young-cancer-victim.html |title=Canada televises funeral of young cancer victim |newspaper=New York Times |date=1981-07-03 |accessdate=2010-02-28}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> a public memorial service was held on [[Parliament Hill]] in Ottawa,<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=haMyAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=3u4FAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=2420,5162646 |title=Memorial service slated for Hill |newspaper=Ottawa Citizen |date=1981-06-30 |accessdate=2010-02-28 |page=8}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> and Canadians again overwhelmed Cancer Society offices with donations.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=haMyAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=3u4FAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=928%2C5160380 |title=Phones 'ringing off wall' pledging cancer donations |newspaper=Ottawa Citizen |date=1981-06-30 |accessdate=2010-02-28 |page=8}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

<h level="2" i="7">==Legacy==</h>
[[File:Terry Fox Run Milan.jpg|thumb|left|Participants of the 2007 Terry Fox Run in Milan, Italy|alt=A police officer on a motorcycle leads runners of all ages down a city street]]

Fox remains a prominent figure in Canadian folklore. His determination united the nation; people from all walks of life lent their support to his run and his memory inspires pride in all regions of the country.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite journal |last=Coupland |first=Douglas |title=Canada's true hero |journal=Macleans Magazine |pages=58–63 |date=2004-07-05 |issn=0024-9262}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> A 1999 national survey named him as Canada's greatest hero,<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite web |url=http://www.sfu.ca/terryfox/about.html |title=About Terry Fox |publisher=Simon Fraser University |accessdate=2010-03-05}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> and he finished second to [[Tommy Douglas]] in the 2004 [[Canadian Broadcasting Corporation]] program ''[[The Greatest Canadian]]''.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://www.cbc.ca/greatest/ |title=The Greatest Canadian |publisher=Canadian Broadcasting Corporation |accessdate=2010-03-05| archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080801091041/http://www.cbc.ca/greatest/| archivedate = August 1, 2008}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Fox's heroic status has been attributed to his image as an ordinary person attempting a remarkable and inspirational feat.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;CFC-Aug1981&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite journal |last1=McCaffery |first1=Margaret |last2=Murray |first2=Terry |title=Terry Fox: Heroes Aren't Saints |journal=Canadian Family Physician |volume=27 |date=August 1981 |pages=1184–1186 |pmc=2306103 |pmid=21289776}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext><ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Rak, 2008, p. 62.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Others have argued that Fox's greatness derives from his audacious vision, his determined pursuit of his goal, his ability to overcome challenges such as his lack of experience and the very loneliness of his venture.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;CFC-Aug1981&quot;</attr></ext><ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite journal|last=Jubas|first=Kaela|year=2006|title= Theorizing Gender in Contemporary Canadian Citizenship: Lessons Learned from the CBC's &quot;Greatest Canadian&quot; Contest|journal=Canadian Journal of Education|volume=29|issue=2|pages=563–583|url=http://www.csse.ca/CJE/KMS/Nov8Jubas.pdf|doi=10.2307/20054177|last2=Jubas|first2=K. }}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> As Fox's advocate on ''The Greatest Canadian'', media personality [[Sook-Yin Lee]] compared him to a classic hero, [[Phidippides]], the runner who delivered the news of the [[Battle of Marathon]] before dying, and asserted that Fox &quot;embodies the most cherished Canadian values: compassion, commitment, perseverance&quot;. She highlighted the juxtaposition between his celebrity, brought about by the unforgettable image he created, and his rejection of the trappings of that celebrity.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Rak, 2008, pp. 62–63.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Typically amongst Canadian icons, Fox is an unconventional hero, admired but not without flaws.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;New&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite book| author = New, William H.| title = Borderlands: how we talk about Canada| url = http://books.google.com/?id=v5nlp2Z2b7IC| date = 1998-06-01| publisher = UBC Press| location = Vancouver| isbn = 978-0-7748-0659-6| pages = 44–45 }}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> An obituary in the ''Canadian Family Physician'' emphasized his humanity and noted that his anger—at his diagnosis, at press misrepresentations and at those he saw as encroaching on his independence—spoke against ascribing sainthood for Fox, and thus placed his achievements within the reach of all.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;CFC-Aug1981&quot;</attr></ext>

<h level="3" i="8">===Attitudes to disability===</h>
Fox expressed a robust attitude to his situation: he refused to regard himself as disabled,<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;isbn0-7295-3673-4&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite book| author = McMurray, Anne| title = Community health and wellness: a socioecological approach| url = http://books.google.com/?id=-F6_n60TCFQC| date = 2003-06-15| publisher = Mosby| location = St. Louis| isbn = 978-0-7295-3673-8| page = 10 }}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> and would not allow anyone to pity him, telling a Toronto radio station that he found life more &quot;rewarding and challenging&quot; since he had lost his leg.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;CFC-Aug1981&quot; </attr></ext> His feat helped redefine Canadian views of disability and the [[Inclusion (disability rights)|inclusion of the disabled]] in society.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://news.therecord.com/article/696082 |title=Terry Fox left a great legacy |newspaper=Kitchener Record |date=2010-04-12 |accessdate=2010-04-24}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext><ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;wheeler&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite book| author = Wheeler, Garry David; Steadward, Robert Daniel; Watkinson, Eddie| coauthors = Elizabeth Jane Watkinson, Garry David Wheeler| title = Adapted physical activity| url = http://books.google.com/?id=u2LvyzEXGMcC| year = 2003| publisher = University of Alberta Press| location = Edmonton, Alberta, Canada| isbn = 978-0-88864-375-9| pages = 36–37 }}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Fox's actions increased the visibility of people with disabilities,<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;wheeler&quot;</attr></ext><ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;isbn978-0-7487-3294-4&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite book| author = Brown, Roy| title = Quality of Life for People With Disabilities: Models, Research and Practice| url = http://books.google.com/?id=1Mxe0YmyTeQC| year = 1997| publisher = Nelson Thornes| location = Cheltenham, U.K| isbn = 978-0-7487-3294-4| page = 255 }}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> and in addition influenced the attitudes of those with disabilities, by showing them disability portrayed in a positive light.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;wheeler&quot;</attr></ext> [[Rick Hansen]] commented that the run challenged society to focus on ability rather than disability. &quot;What was perceived as a limitation became a great opportunity. People with disabilities started looking at things differently. They came away with huge pride&quot;, he wrote.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;s227&quot;</attr><inner>Scrivener, 2000, p. 227.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

In contrast, the narrative surrounding Fox has been critiqued as illustrating the media's focus on stereotyped portrayals of the heroic and extraordinary achievements of people with disabilities, rather than more mundane accomplishments.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Nelson&quot;</attr></ext><ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;isbn0-275-97943-1&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite book| author = Smith, Linda C.; King, Gillian A.; Brown, Elizabeth Mills| title = Resilience: learning from people with disabilities and the turning points in their lives| url = http://books.google.com/?id=JNrqSQqvbB8C| date = 2003-10| publisher = Praeger| location = New York| isbn = 978-0-275-97943-0| page = 81 }}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Actor [[Alan Toy]] noted &quot;Sure, it raised money for cancer research and sure it showed the human capacity for achievement. But a lot of disabled people are made to feel like failures if they haven't done something extraordinary. They may be bankers or factory workers – proof enough of their usefulness to society. Do we have to be 'supercrips' in order to be valid? And if we're not super, are we invalid?&quot;<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Nelson&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite book| author = Nelson, Jack A.| coauthors = Susan Dente Ross| title = Images that injure: pictorial stereotypes in the media| url = http://books.google.com/?id=x4yjcIocJAkC| year = 2003| publisher = Praeger| location = New York| isbn = 978-0-275-97846-4| chapter = The invisible cultural group: Images of disability }}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> The media's idealization of Fox has also been critiqued for emphasizing an individualistic approach to illness and disability, in which the body is a machine to be mastered, rather than the [[social model of disability]], where societal attitudes and barriers to inclusion play a prominent role in determining who is disabled.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;isbn978-0-7619-4730-1&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite book| author = Seale, Clive| title = Media and health| url = http://books.google.com/?id=pWF_3ydQ4QUC| year = 2002| publisher = Sage| location = Thousand Oaks, Calif| isbn = 978-0-7619-4730-1| page = 112 }}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext><ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite journal|last=Harrison|first=Deborah|year=1985|title=The Terry Fox story and the popular media: a case study in ideology and illness|journal= Canadian Review of Sociology |volume=22|issue=4|pages=496–514|doi=10.1111/j.1755-618X.1985.tb00378.x}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

<h level="3" i="9">===Terry Fox Run===</h>
<template lineStart="1"><title>main</title><part><name index="1"/><value>Terry Fox Run</value></part></template>
One of Fox's earliest supporters was [[Isadore Sharp]], founder of the [[Four Seasons Hotels and Resorts|Four Seasons Hotels]]. Sharp had lost his own son to cancer and offered Fox and his companions free accommodation at his hotels.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Greatest Canadian&quot; </attr></ext> He donated $10,000 and challenged 999 other businesses to do the same.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Marathon&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite web |last=Scrivener |first=Leslie |url=http://www.terryfox.org/Foundation/The_Marathon_of_Hope.html |title=Marathon of Hope |publisher=The Terry Fox Foundation |accessdate=2010-03-01}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Sharp also proposed an annual fundraising run in Fox's name. Fox agreed, but insisted that the runs be non-competitive. There were to be no winners or losers, and anyone who participated could run, walk or ride.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Scrivener187&quot;</attr><inner>Scrivener, 2000, p. 187.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Sharp faced opposition to the project. The Cancer Society feared that a fall run would detract from its traditional April campaigns, while other charities believed that an additional fundraiser would leave less money for their causes.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Millionaire&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite news |last=Scrivener |first=Terry |title=A millionaire keeps Terry's memory alive |newspaper=Toronto Star |date=1987-09-13 |page=D1}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Sharp persisted, and he, the Four Seasons Hotels and the Fox family organized the first Terry Fox Run on September 13, 1981.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Scrivener187&quot; </attr></ext>

Over 300,000 people took part and raised $3.5 million in the first Terry Fox Run.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Marathon&quot; </attr></ext> Schools across Canada were urged to join the second run, held on September 19, 1982.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=EQowAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=AqUFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=1975,3873773 |title=Join Fox run, schools urged |newspaper=Montreal Gazette |date=1982-08-17 |accessdate=2010-03-01 |page=A11}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> School participation has continued since, evolving into the National School Run Day.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite web |url=http://www.opsba.org/index.php?q=news/terry_fox_run_largest_event_in_canadian_history |title=Terry Fox Run – Largest event in Canadian history |publisher=Ontario Public School Boards Association |date=2005-03-01 |accessdate=2010-03-01}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> The runs, which raised over $20 million in its first six years,<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Millionaire&quot; </attr></ext> grew into an international event as over one million people in 60 countries took part in 1999, raising $15 million that year alone.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://www.cbc.ca/canada/story/1999/09/19/foxrun990919.html |title=Terry Fox's memory, goal live on |publisher=Canadian Broadcasting Corporation |date=1999-09-19 |accessdate=2010-03-01}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> By the Terry Fox Run's 25th anniversary, more than three million people were taking part annually. Grants from the Terry Fox Foundation, which organizes the runs, have helped Canadian scientists make numerous advances in cancer research.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://www.cbc.ca/canada/story/2005/09/17/Fox_2520050917.html |title=Canadians celebrate the life of Terry Fox |publisher=Canadian Broadcasting Corporation |date=2005-09-17 |accessdate=2010-03-01}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> The Terry Fox Run is the world's largest one-day fundraiser for cancer research,<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite web |last=El Shammaa |first=Dina |url=http://gulfnews.com/news/gulf/uae/health/terry-fox-never-gave-up-and-had-positive-attitude-1.584178 |title=Terry Fox 'never gave up and had positive attitude' |publisher=Gulf News |date=2010-02-17 |accessdate=2010-03-07}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> and over $500 million has been raised in his name.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite web |url=http://www.terryfox.org/Foundation/The_Terry_Fox_Foundation.html |title=Mission statement &amp; history |publisher=The Terry Fox Foundation |accessdate=2010-03-01}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> The 30th Terry Fox Run was held September 19, 2010.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |last=Gamble |first=Susan |url=http://www.brantfordexpositor.ca/ArticleDisplay.aspx?e=1693638 |title=Organizers launch promotion of Terry Fox Run on Saturday |newspaper=Brantford Expositor |accessdate=2010-03-01}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

<h level="3" i="10">===Honours===</h>
[[File:Terry Fox.jpg|thumb|right|[[Terry Fox Memorial and Lookout|Memorial]] erected outside of [[Thunder Bay]] on the Trans Canada Highway near the spot where Fox was forced to end his marathon.|alt=Statue of a runner with an artificial leg looking skyward.]]
The physical memorials in Canada named after Fox include:<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |title=How Terry Fox changed Canada |first=Leslie |last=Scrivener |newspaper=Toronto Star |date=2010-04-11 |url=http://www.thestar.com/news/canada/article/793452--how-terry-fox-changed-canada |accessdate=2010-04-20}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>
* Approximately 32 roads and streets, including the [[Thunder Bay Expressway|Terry Fox Courage Highway]] near Thunder Bay, near where Fox ended his run and where an oversized statue of him was erected as a monument;<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;FoxHansen&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite news |last=Wilkes |first=Jim |title=Hansen stops to honor Terry's dream of hope |newspaper=Toronto Star |date=1987-01-05 |page=A2}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>
* 14 schools, including a new school in a suburb of Montreal that was renamed Terry Fox Elementary School shortly after he died,<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=Qo0kAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=bLkFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=1180,1867787 |title=Terry Fox 'better name' for school than Fathers |newspaper=Montreal Gazette |date=1981-11-06 |accessdate=2010-03-03 |page=3}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> and the Port Coquitlam high school, from which he had graduated, which was renamed [[Terry Fox Secondary School]] on 18 January 1986;<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite web |url=http://public.sd43.bc.ca/secondary/terryfox/about_us/General%20Info%20Documents/The%20Terry%20Fox%20Story.pdf |title=The Terry Fox story |format=PDF |publisher=Terry Fox Secondary School |accessdate=2010-03-03|archiveurl = http://www.webcitation.org/5o4OymYFe |archivedate = 2010-03-08|deadurl=yes}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>
* 14 other buildings, including many athletic centres and the Terry Fox Research Institute in Vancouver;
* Seven statues, including the Terry Fox Monument in Ottawa, which was the genesis of ''The Path of Heroes'', a federal government initiative that seeks to honour the people that shaped the nation;<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;TFFFacts&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite web |url=http://www.terryfox.org/Foundation/Facts.html |title=Facts |publisher=The Terry Fox Foundation |accessdate=2010-03-05}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>
* nine fitness trails;
* A previously unnamed mountain in the [[Rocky Mountains|Canadian Rockies]] in the [[Selwyn Range (British Columbia)|Selwyn range]], which was named [[Mount Terry Fox]] by the government of British Columbia;<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=eaMyAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=3O4FAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4905,2432798 |title=Mountain in Rockies named for Terry Fox |newspaper=Ottawa Citizen |date=1981-07-07 |accessdate=2010-03-05 |page=16}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> the area around it is now known as [[Mount Terry Fox Provincial Park]]; 
* The &quot;Terry Fox Fountain of Hope&quot; was installed in 1982 on the historic grounds of [[Rideau Hall]], the official residence of the [[Governor General of Canada]];<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news|last=Howell|first=Elizabeth|title=Rideau Hall grounds to get $2.5M facelift|url=http://www.obj.ca/Real-Estate/Construction/2012-05-11/article-2976604/Rideau-Hall-grounds-to-get-$2.5M-facelift/1|accessdate=24 July 2012|newspaper=[[Ottawa Business Journal]]|date=11 May 2012}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> 
* The [[Canadian Coast Guard]] [[icebreaker]] [[CCGS Terry Fox|CCGS ''Terry Fox'']], which was commissioned in 1983; and<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite web |url=http://www.ccg-gcc.gc.ca/eng/Fleet/Vessels?id=982&amp;info=1 |title=CGCS Terry Fox |publisher=Fisheries and Oceans Canada |accessdate=2010-03-05}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>
* In 2011, a series of bronze sculptures of Fox in motion, designed by author [[Douglas Coupland]] and depicting Fox running toward the Pacific Ocean, was unveiled outside of [[BC Place]] in downtown Vancouver.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news|title=New Terry Fox memorial unveiled in Vancouver|url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/british-columbia/story/2011/09/16/bc-terry-fox-memorial.html|publisher=CBC News|accessdate=16 September 2011|date=2011-09-16}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

Shortly after his death, Fox was named the Newsmaker of the Year for 1981,<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |title=Poll again names Fox Canadian of the Year |newspaper=Montreal Gazette |date=1981-12-18 |page=13}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> and [[Canada Post]] announced the production of a commemorative stamp in 1981, bypassing its traditionally held position that stamps honouring people should not be created until ten years after their deaths.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |last=Krebs |first=Albin |last2=Thomas |first2=Robert |url=http://www.nytimes.com/1981/06/27/nyregion/notes-on-people-176204.html |title=Canada finds way to honor Terry Fox with a Stamp |newspaper=New York Times |date=1981-06-27 |accessdate=2010-03-02}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> British rock star [[Rod Stewart]] was so moved by the Marathon of Hope that he was inspired to write and dedicate the song &quot;Never Give Up on a Dream&quot; — found on his 1981 album ''[[Tonight I'm Yours]]'' — to Fox. Stewart also called his 1981–1982 tour of Canada the &quot;Terry Fox Tour&quot;.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=4FsxAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=DaUFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5500,1321811 |title=Rod Stewart writes a song for Terry Fox |newspaper=Montreal Gazette |date=1981-11-13 |accessdate=2010-03-02 |page=48}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

The [[Terry Fox Hall of Fame]] was established in 1994 to recognize individuals that have made contributions that improved the quality of life of disabled people.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;TFFFacts&quot;</attr></ext><ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite web |url=http://www.canparaplegic.org/en/Advocacy_34/Disability_Organizations_1751/18.html |title=Terry Fox Hall of Fame |publisher=Canadian Paraplegic Association |accessdate=2010-04-24}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> The [[Terry Fox Laboratory]] research centre was established in Vancouver to conduct leading edge research into the causes and potential cures for cancer.

The [[Royal Canadian Mint]] produced a special dollar coin in 2005 to commemorate the 25th anniversary of the Marathon of Hope. It was their first regular circulation coin to feature a Canadian.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://www.cbc.ca/canada/story/2005/03/14/terry-fox050314.html |title=Dollar coin honours Terry Fox |publisher=Canadian Broadcasting Corporation |date=2005-03-14 |accessdate=2010-03-05}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> 

In 2008, Terry Fox was named a [[Persons of National Historic Significance|National Historic Person of Canada]], a recognition given by the [[Government of Canada|Canadian government]] to those persons who are considered to have played a nationally significant role in the history of the country.  Fox's designation was due to his status as an &quot;enduring icon&quot;, his personal qualities, and for the manner in which the Marathon of Hope had captivated the country and resonated deeply with Canadians.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{DFHD|12011|Fox, Terry National Historic Person|24 July 2012}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

Fox's mother, [[Betty Fox]], was one of eight people to carry the [[Olympic Flag]] into [[BC Place Stadium]] at the [[2010 Winter Olympics opening ceremony|opening ceremonies]] of the [[2010 Winter Olympics]] in [[Vancouver]].<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |last=Bartel |first=Kate |url=http://www.bclocalnews.com/tri_city_maple_ridge/tricitynews/news/84509327.html |title=Fox: 'I was there in place of Terry' |newspaper=Tri-City News |date=2010-02-16 |accessdate=2010-03-05|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20100430023227/http://www.bclocalnews.com/tri_city_maple_ridge/tricitynews/news/84509327.html |archivedate = April 30, 2010|deadurl=yes}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> The games saw the [[Terry Fox Award]] bestowed on Olympic athletes who embodied Fox's characteristics of determination and humility in the face of adversity.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://www.cbc.ca/canada/british-columbia/story/2009/12/11/bc-terry-fox-vancouver-olympic-award.html |title=Terry Fox Award to recognize courageous Olympic athlete |publisher=Canadian Broadcasting Corporation |date=2009-12-11 |accessdate=2010-03-19}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

<h level="3" i="11">===Films===</h>
Fox's story was dramatized in the 1983 [[biopic]] ''[[The Terry Fox Story]]''. Produced by [[Home Box Office]], the film aired as a [[television movie]] in the United States and had a theatrical run in Canada.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;1983FilmReviews&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite news |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=6kMwAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=QaUFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4415,1524323 |title=More raves than boos for 'Terry Fox Story' |newspaper=Montreal Gazette |date=1983-05-24 |accessdate=2010-03-06 |page=D10}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> The film starred amputee actor [[Eric Fryer]] and [[Robert Duvall]], and was the first film made exclusively for pay television.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=A68yAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=6-4FAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4635,4356556 |title='People will remember this...' |newspaper=Ottawa Citizen |date=1982-09-20 |accessdate=2010-03-06 |page=37}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> The movie received mixed but generally positive reviews.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;1983FilmReviews&quot; </attr></ext> However, it was criticized by Fox's family over how it portrayed his temper.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;MacleansFilm&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite news |last=McKay |first=John |url=http://www.macleans.ca/culture/entertainment/article.jsp?content=20050912_112057_112059 |title=Terry Fox: A hero's story |newspaper=Macleans Magazine |date=2005-09-09 |accessdate=2010-03-06}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> ''The Terry Fox Story'' was nominated for eight [[Genie Awards]], and won five, including [[Genie Award for Best Motion Picture|Best Picture]] and [[Genie Award for Best Performance by an Actor in a Leading Role|Best Actor]].<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |last=Lawson |first=Michael |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=l74yAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=S-8FAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=1697,1159491 |title=Terry Fox Story awarded best picture, actor Genies |newspaper=Ottawa Citizen |date=1984-03-22 |accessdate=2010-03-06 |page=93}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

A second movie, titled ''[[Terry (film)|Terry]]'', focused on the Marathon of Hope, was produced by the [[CTV Television Network]] in 2005. Fox was portrayed by [[Shawn Ashmore]]. He is not an amputee; digital editing was used to superimpose a prosthesis over his real leg. The film was endorsed by Fox's family, and portrayed his attitude more positively than the first movie.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;MacleansFilm&quot; </attr></ext> Canadian [[National Basketball Association]] star [[Steve Nash]], who himself was inspired by Fox when he was a child, directed a 2010 documentary ''Into the Wind'', which aired on [[ESPN]] as part of its ''[[30 for 30]]'' series.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite web |url=http://www.canada.com/vancouversun/news/westcoastnews/story.html?id=006545a4-a2d6-4867-9adf-d60125176f14 |title=Nash to make film about Terry Fox |work=Vancouver Sun |date=2008-07-12 |accessdate=2010-03-06}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext><ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite web |url=http://30for30.espn.com/film/into-the-wind.html |title=Into the Wind |publisher=ESPN |accessdate=2010-03-06}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

<h level="3" i="12">===Steve Fonyo and Rick Hansen===</h>
Terry Fox was not the first person to attempt to run across Canada. [[Mark Kent]] crossed the country in 1974 as he raised money for the Canadian team at the [[1976 Summer Olympics]].<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;MtlGazette42880&quot; </attr></ext><ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=EYY0AAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=7qEFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4860,3621025 |title=Run across Canada with Mark |newspaper=Montreal Gazette |date=1974-09-27 |accessdate=2010-03-03 |page=4}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> While he lived, Fox refused to let anyone else complete the Marathon of Hope, having promised to finish it himself once he recovered.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Scrivener187&quot; </attr></ext> [[Steve Fonyo]], an 18-year-old who suffered from the same form of cancer and who also had a leg amputated, sought in 1984 to duplicate Fox's run, calling his effort the &quot;Journey for Lives&quot;.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=-BciAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=kKUFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=997,1844598 |title=Amputee will follow Terry Fox |newspaper=Montreal Gazette |date=1984-03-17 |accessdate=2010-03-03 |page=C4}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> After leaving St. John's on March 31, Fonyo reached the point where Fox was forced to end his marathon at the end of November,<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=GyAyAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=q6UFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4381,7052496 |title=Fonyo passes spot where Terry Fox abandoned his run |newspaper=Montreal Gazette |date=1984-11-30 |accessdate=2010-03-03 |page=B1}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> and completed the transcontinental run on May 29, 1985.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=RBgiAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=1aUFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4673%2C3845907 |title=14-month Journey for Lives ends today |newspaper=Montreal Gazette |date=1985-05-29 |accessdate=2010-03-03 |page=B1}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> The Journey for Lives raised over $13 million for cancer research.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |last=Kidd |first=Kenneth |url=http://www.thestar.com/news/insight/article/758227--steve-fonyo-out-of-order |title=Steve Fonyo: Out of Order |newspaper=Toronto Star |date=2010-01-31 |accessdate=2010-03-03}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

Canadian [[Paralympic Games|Paralympic]] athlete [[Rick Hansen]], who had recruited Fox to play on his wheelchair basketball team in 1977, was similarly inspired by the Marathon of Hope.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite web |url=http://www.histori.ca/minutes/minute.do?id=14214 |title=Footprints: Rick Hansen |publisher=Historica-Dominion Institute of Canada |accessdate=2010-03-03}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Hansen, who first considered circumnavigating the globe in his wheelchair in 1974, began the [[Man in Motion World Tour]] in 1985 with the goal of raising $10 million towards research into [[spinal cord injuries]].<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |last=Stallings |first=Dianne |url=http://news.google.ca/newspapers?id=XLwMAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=smYDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=2882,3949717 |title=Wheelchair marathoner rolls through on tour of the world |newspaper=St. Petersburg Times |date=1985-06-19 |accessdate=2010-03-03 |page=1}} {{Dead link|date=March 2012|bot=H3llBot}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> As Fonyo had, Hansen paused at the spot Fox's run ended to honour the late runner.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;FoxHansen&quot; </attr></ext> Hansen completed his world tour in May 1987 after 792 days and <template><title>convert</title><part><name index="1"/><value>40073</value></part><part><name index="2"/><value>km</value></part><part><name index="3"/><value>mi</value></part></template>;<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |title=Hansen's heroic feat |newspaper=Toronto Star |date=1987-05-22 |page=A18}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> he travelled through 34 countries and raised over $26 million.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news |last=Kassam |first=Ashifa |url=http://www.thestar.com/News/article/223493 |title=Rick Hansen to be inducted into Canada's Walk of Fame |newspaper=Toronto Star |date=2007-06-09 |accessdate=2010-03-03}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

<h level="2" i="13">==See also==</h>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Portal</title><part><name index="1"/><value>History of Canada</value></part><part><name index="2"/><value>Biography</value></part></template>
* [[Terry (book)|''Terry'' (book)]]
<template lineStart="1"><title>-</title></template>

<h level="2" i="14">==References==</h>
;Footnotes
<template lineStart="1"><title>Reflist</title><part><name>colwidth</name><equals>=</equals><value>30em</value></part></template>
;Bibliography
<template lineStart="1"><title>refbegin</title></template>
* <template><title>cite book</title><part><name> author </name><equals>=</equals><value> Leslie Scrivener</value></part><part><name> last </name><equals>=</equals><value> Scrivener</value></part><part><name> first </name><equals>=</equals><value> Leslie</value></part><part><name> title </name><equals>=</equals><value> Terry Fox: His Story</value></part><part><name> url </name><equals>=</equals><value> http://books.google.com/?id=XG5glHczVt0C</value></part><part><name> date </name><equals>=</equals><value> 2000-09-01</value></part><part><name> publisher </name><equals>=</equals><value> McClelland &amp; Stewart</value></part><part><name> location </name><equals>=</equals><value> Toronto</value></part><part><name> isbn </name><equals>=</equals><value> 978-0-7710-8019-7 </value></part></template>
* <template><title>cite book </title><part><name>last</name><equals>=</equals><value>Coupland </value></part><part><name>first</name><equals>=</equals><value>Douglas </value></part><part><name>title</name><equals>=</equals><value>Terry </value></part><part><name>publisher</name><equals>=</equals><value>Douglas &amp; McIntyre </value></part><part><name>location</name><equals>=</equals><value>Vancouver </value></part><part><name>year</name><equals>=</equals><value>2005 </value></part><part><name>isbn</name><equals>=</equals><value>978-1-55365-113-0</value></part></template>
* <template><title>cite book</title><part><name> author </name><equals>=</equals><value> Angela Murphy</value></part><part><name> last </name><equals>=</equals><value> Murphy</value></part><part><name> first </name><equals>=</equals><value> Angela</value></part><part><name> title </name><equals>=</equals><value> Great Canadians</value></part><part><name> url </name><equals>=</equals><value> http://books.google.com/?id=y_M3GwAACAAJ</value></part><part><name> date </name><equals>=</equals><value> 2005-06-30</value></part><part><name> publisher </name><equals>=</equals><value> Folklore Publishing</value></part><part><name> location </name><equals>=</equals><value> Canada</value></part><part><name> isbn </name><equals>=</equals><value> 978-1-894864-46-6 </value></part></template>
* <template><title>cite book</title><part><name> author </name><equals>=</equals><value> Zoë Druick</value></part><part><name> last </name><equals>=</equals><value> Rak</value></part><part><name> first </name><equals>=</equals><value> Julie</value></part><part><name> coauthors </name><equals>=</equals><value> Aspa Kotsopoulos</value></part><part><name> title </name><equals>=</equals><value> Programming Reality</value></part><part><name> url </name><equals>=</equals><value> http://books.google.com/?id=UIkaWHBUZywC</value></part><part><name> date </name><equals>=</equals><value> 2008-08-01</value></part><part><name> publisher </name><equals>=</equals><value> Wilfrid Laurier University Press</value></part><part><name> location </name><equals>=</equals><value> Canada</value></part><part><name> isbn </name><equals>=</equals><value> 978-1-55458-010-1</value></part><part><name> chapter </name><equals>=</equals><value> Canadian Idols? CBC's The Greatest Canadian as Celebrity History </value></part></template>
<template lineStart="1"><title>refend</title></template>

<h level="2" i="15">==External links==</h>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Commons category</title></template>
* [http://www.terryfox.org/ The Terry Fox Foundation]
* [http://www.cbc.ca/archives/categories/sports/exploits/terry-fox-25-reliving-the-marathon-of-hope/topic---terry-fox-25-reliving-the-marathon-of-hope.html CBC Digital Archives – Terry Fox 25: Reliving the Marathon of Hope]
* [http://www.bcsportshalloffame.com BC Sports Hall of Fame and Museum]
*[http://thecanadianencyclopedia.com/featured/the-courage-of-terry-fox The Canadian Encyclopedia, The Courage of Terry Fox]

<template lineStart="1"><title>s-start</title></template>
<template lineStart="1"><title>s-ach</title><part><name index="1"/><value>aw</value></part></template>
<template lineStart="1"><title>succession box
</title><part><name> title</name><equals>=</equals><value>[[Lou Marsh Trophy|Lou Marsh Trophy winner]]
</value></part><part><name> before</name><equals>=</equals><value>[[Sandra Post]]
</value></part><part><name> years</name><equals>=</equals><value>1980
</value></part><part><name> after</name><equals>=</equals><value>[[Susan Nattrass]]
</value></part></template>
<template lineStart="1"><title>s-end</title></template>

<template lineStart="1"><title>featured article</title></template>

<comment>&lt;!--{{Authority control|LCCN=n/81/099908}}--&gt;
</comment>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Persondata <comment>&lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;</comment> 
</title><part><name>NAME </name><equals>=</equals><value> Fox, Terrence Stanley
</value></part><part><name>ALTERNATIVE NAMES </name><equals>=</equals><value> Terry Fox
</value></part><part><name>SHORT DESCRIPTION </name><equals>=</equals><value> Canadian athlete and cancer activist
</value></part><part><name>DATE OF BIRTH </name><equals>=</equals><value> 28 July 1958
</value></part><part><name>PLACE OF BIRTH </name><equals>=</equals><value> [[Winnipeg]], [[Manitoba]]
</value></part><part><name>DATE OF DEATH </name><equals>=</equals><value> 28 June 1981
</value></part><part><name>PLACE OF DEATH </name><equals>=</equals><value> [[Port Coquitlam]], [[British Columbia]]
</value></part></template>
<template lineStart="1"><title>DEFAULTSORT:Fox, Terry</title></template>
[[Category:Terry Fox| ]]
[[Category:1958 births]]
[[Category:1981 deaths]]
[[Category:Canadian basketball players]]
[[Category:Canadian humanitarians]]
[[Category:Canada's Sports Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:Companions of the Order of Canada]]
[[Category:Lou Marsh Trophy winners]]
[[Category:Sportspeople from British Columbia]]
[[Category:People from Port Coquitlam]]
[[Category:Sportspeople from Winnipeg]]
[[Category:Simon Fraser University alumni]]
[[Category:Canadian amputees]]
[[Category:Canadian disabled sportspeople]]
[[Category:Persons of National Historic Significance (Canada)]]
[[Category:Canadian Newsmakers of the Year]]
[[Category:Deaths from lung cancer]]
[[Category:Deaths from bone cancer]]

[[ar:تيري فوكس]]
[[zh-min-nan:Terry Fox]]
[[cs:Terry Fox]]
[[da:Terry Fox]]
[[de:Terry Fox (Leichtathlet)]]
[[et:Terry Fox]]
[[es:Terry Fox]]
[[eo:Terry Fox]]
[[fr:Terry Fox]]
[[ko:테리 폭스]]
[[hr:Terry Fox]]
[[it:Terry Fox]]
[[lv:Terijs Fokss]]
[[ms:Terry Fox]]
[[nl:Terry Fox]]
[[ja:テリー・フォックス]]
[[no:Terry Fox]]
[[pl:Terry Fox]]
[[pt:Terry Fox]]
[[ru:Фокс, Терри]]
[[simple:Terry Fox]]
[[sr:Тери Фокс]]
[[fi:Terry Fox]]
[[sv:Terry Fox]]
[[ta:டெர்ரி பாக்ஸ்]]
[[tr:Terry Fox]]
[[uk:Террі Фокс]]
[[vi:Terry Fox]]
[[zh:泰瑞·福克斯]]</root>