<root><template><title>Infobox_Disease
 </title><part><name> Name           </name><equals>=</equals><value> Gaucher&amp;#39;s disease
 </value></part><part><name> Image          </name><equals>=</equals><value> 
 </value></part><part><name> Caption        </name><equals>=</equals><value> 
 </value></part><part><name> DiseasesDB     </name><equals>=</equals><value> 5124
 </value></part><part><name> ICD10          </name><equals>=</equals><value> <template><title>ICD10</title><part><name index="1"/><value>E</value></part><part><name index="2"/><value>75</value></part><part><name index="3"/><value>2</value></part><part><name index="4"/><value>e</value></part><part><name index="5"/><value>70</value></part></template> ([[ILDS]] E75.220)
 </value></part><part><name> ICD9           </name><equals>=</equals><value> <template><title>ICD9</title><part><name index="1"/><value>272.7</value></part></template>
 </value></part><part><name> OMIM           </name><equals>=</equals><value> 230800
 </value></part><part><name> OMIM_mult      </name><equals>=</equals><value> <template><title>OMIM2</title><part><name index="1"/><value>230900</value></part></template> <template><title>OMIM2</title><part><name index="1"/><value>231000</value></part></template>
 </value></part><part><name> MedlinePlus    </name><equals>=</equals><value> 000564
 </value></part><part><name> eMedicineSubj  </name><equals>=</equals><value> ped
 </value></part><part><name> eMedicineTopic </name><equals>=</equals><value> 837
 </value></part><part><name> eMedicine_mult </name><equals>=</equals><value> <template><title>eMedicine2</title><part><name index="1"/><value>derm</value></part><part><name index="2"/><value>709</value></part></template>
 </value></part><part><name> MeshID         </name><equals>=</equals><value> D005776
</value></part></template>

'''Gaucher's disease''' (<template><title>pron-en</title><part><name index="1"/><value>goʊˈʃeɪz dɨziːz</value></part></template>) is the most common of the [[lysosomal storage disease]]s. It is caused by a deficiency of the enzyme [[glucocerebrosidase]], leading to an accumulation of its substrate, the fatty substance [[cerebroside|glucocerebroside]] (also known as [[glucosylceramide]]). Fatty material can collect in the [[spleen]], liver, [[kidney]]s, [[lung]]s, [[brain]] and bone marrow. Symptoms may include enlarged spleen and liver, liver malfunction, [[List of skeletal disorders|skeletal disorders]] and bone lesions that may be painful, severe [[Neurology|neurologic]] complications, swelling of [[lymph node]]s and (occasionally) adjacent joints, distended abdomen, a brownish tint to the skin, [[anemia]], low blood [[platelet]]s and yellow fatty deposits on the [[sclera]]. Persons affected most seriously may also be more susceptible to infection. The disease shows [[autosomal recessive]] inheritance and therefore affects both males and females. It is [[eponym|named after]] the French doctor [[Philippe Gaucher]] who originally described it in 1882.  <ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Gaucher PCE. ''De l'epithelioma primitif de la rate, hypertrophie idiopathique de la rate sans leucemie''. Academic thesis, Paris, France, 1882.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> The biochemical basis for the disease would be elucidated in [[1965]] by Brady ''et al''.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite journal |author=Brady RO, Kanfer JN, Shapiro D |title=Metabolism of glucocerebrosides. II. Evidence of an enzymatic deficiency in Gaucher's disease |journal=Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. |volume=18 |issue= |pages=221–5 |year=1965 |pmid=14282020|doi=10.1016/0006-291X(65)90743-6}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>  The first effective treatment for the disease, the drug Ceredase, was approved by the FDA in June 1995.  An improved drug, Cerezyme, was approved by the FDA in 2001 and has replaced the use of Ceredase.


<h level="2" i="1">== Subtypes ==</h>
Gaucher's disease has three common clinical subtypes.

* Type I (or nonneuropathic type) is the most common form of the disease, occurring in approximately 1 in 50,000 live births. It occurs most often among persons of [[Ashkenazi Jews|Ashkenazi Jewish]] heritage. Symptoms may begin early in life or in adulthood and include [[hepatomegaly|enlarged liver]] and grossly [[splenomegaly|enlarged spleen]] (together [[hepatosplenomegaly]]); the spleen can rupture and cause additional complications. Skeletal weakness and bone disease may be extensive. Spleen enlargement and bone marrow replacement cause [[anemia]], thrombocytopenia and [[leukopenia]]. The brain is not affected, but there may be lung and, rarely, kidney impairment. Patients in this group usually [[bruise]] easily and experience fatigue due to low blood platelets. Depending on disease onset and severity, type 1 patients may live well into adulthood. Many patients have a mild form of the disease or may not show any symptoms.

* Type II (or acute infantile neuropathic Gaucher's disease) typically begins within 6 months of birth and has an incidence rate of approximately 1 in 100,000 live births. Symptoms include an enlarged liver and spleen, extensive and progressive brain damage, eye movement disorders, [[spasticity]], [[seizure]]s, limb rigidity, and a poor ability to suck and swallow. Affected children usually die by age 2.

* Type III (the chronic neuropathic form) can begin at any time in childhood or even in adulthood, and occurs in approximately 1 in 100,000 live births. It is characterized by slowly progressive but milder neurologic symptoms compared to the acute or type 2 version. Major symptoms include an enlarged spleen and/or liver, seizures, poor coordination, skeletal irregularities, eye movement disorders, blood disorders including anemia and respiratory problems. Patients often live into their early teen years and adulthood.

These subtypes have come under some criticism for not taking account of the spectrum of observable symptoms (the [[phenotypes]].[http://www.gaucher.org.uk/consenmarch2002.htm]) There are also compound heterozygous variations which considerably increase the complexity of predicting disease course.

<h level="2" i="2">==Signs and symptoms==</h>
* Painless [[hepatomegaly]] and [[splenomegaly]]; the size of the spleen can be 1500-3000 ml, as opposed to the normal size of 50-200 ml.
* [[Hypersplenism]]: the rapid and premature destruction of blood cells, leading to [[anemia]], [[neutropenia]] and [[thrombocytopenia]] (with an increased  risk of [[infection]] and [[bleeding]])
* [[Cirrhosis]] of the liver is rare
* [[Neurology|Neurological]] symptoms occur only in some types of Gaucher's (see below):
** Type II: serious convulsions, hypertonia, mental retardation, apnea.
** Type III: muscle twitches known as [[myoclonus]], convulsions, dementia, ocular muscle apraxia.
* [[Osteoporosis]]: 75% develop visible bony abnormalities due to the accumulated glucosylceramide. A deformity of the distal [[femur]] in the shape of an [[Erlenmeyer flask]]  is commonly described.
* Yellowish-brown skin [[pigmentation]]

<h level="2" i="3">==Diagnosis==</h>
A definitive diagnosis is made with [[genetic test]]ing.  As there are numerous different mutations, sequencing of the beta-glucosidase gene is sometimes necessary to confirm the diagnosis. Prenatal diagnosis is available, and is useful when there is a known genetic risk factor.

A diagnosis can also be implied by biochemical abnormalities such as high [[alkaline phosphatase]], [[angiotensin-converting enzyme]] (ACE) and [[immunoglobulin]] levels, or by cell analysis showing &quot;crinkled paper&quot; cytoplasm and glycolipid-laden macrophages.

<h level="2" i="4">==Pathophysiology==</h>
[[Image:Acid beta glucosidase.png|framed|right|200px|Acid beta-glucosidase]]The disease is caused by a defect in the [[housekeeping gene]] ''lysosomal gluco-cerebrosidase'' (also known as beta-glucosidase, <template><title>EC number</title><part><name index="1"/><value>3.2.1.45</value></part></template>, <template><title>PDB</title><part><name index="1"/><value>1OGS</value></part></template>) on the first [[chromosome]] (1q21). The [[enzyme]] is a 55.6 [[kilodalton|KD]], 497 [[amino acid]]s long protein that catalyses the breakdown of [[glucocerebroside]], a [[cell membrane]] constituent of red and white blood cells. The [[macrophage]]s that clear these cells are unable to eliminate the waste product, which accumulates in fibrils, and turn into ''Gaucher cells'', which appear on [[light microscopy]] to resemble crumpled-up paper.

Different mutations in the beta-glucosidase determine the remaining activity of the enzyme, and, to a large extent, the [[phenotype]].

In the brain (type II and III), glucocerebroside accumulates due to the turnover of complex [[lipid]]s during brain development and the formation of the [[myelin sheath]] of nerves.

Research suggests that heterozygotes for particular acid beta-glucosidase mutations are at an increased risk of [[Parkinson's disease]].<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite journal |author=Aharon-Peretz J, Rosenbaum H, Gershoni-Baruch R |title=Mutations in the glucocerebrosidase gene and Parkinson's disease in Ashkenazi Jews |journal=N. Engl. J. Med. |volume=351 |issue=19 |pages=1972–7 |year=2004 |pmid=15525722 |doi=10.1056/NEJMoa033277}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> A study of 1525 Gaucher patients in the [[United States]] suggested that while cancer risk is not elevated, particular malignancies ([[non-Hodgkin lymphoma]], [[melanoma]] and [[pancreatic cancer]]) occurred at a 2-3 times higher rate.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite journal |author=Landgren O, Turesson I, Gridley G, Caporaso NE |title=Risk of Malignant Disease Among 1525 Adult Male US Veterans With Gaucher Disease |journal= Archives of Internal Medicine|volume=167 |issue=11 |pages=1189–1194 |year=2007 |pmid=17563029 |doi=10.1001/archinte.167.11.1189}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

<h level="2" i="5">==Classification and genetics==</h>
The three types of Gaucher's disease are inherited in an [[autosomal recessive]] fashion. Both parents must be carriers in order for a child to be affected. If both parents are carriers, there is a one in four, or 25%, chance with each pregnancy for an affected child. [[Genetic counseling]] and [[genetic testing]] is recommended for families who may be carriers of mutations.

Each type has been linked to particular mutations. In all, there are about 80 known mutations, grouped into three main types:<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{OMIM|606463}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>
* Type I (N370S [[homozygote]]), the most common, also called the &quot;non-neuropathic&quot; type occurs mainly in [[Ashkenazi|Ashkenazi Jews]], at 100 times the occurence in the general populace. The median age at diagnosis is 28 years of age,<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Grabowski2008&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite journal|journal=Lancet|year=2008|volume=372|pages=1263&amp;ndash;1271
|doi=10.1016/S0140-6736(08)61522-6|title=Phenotype, diagnosis, and treatment of Gaucher's disease|author=Grabowski GA}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> and life expectancy is mildly decreased. There are no neurological symptoms.
* Type II (1 or 2 [[allele]]s L444P) is characterized by neurological problems in small children. The enzyme is hardly released into the [[lysosome]]s. Prognosis is dismal: most die before reaching the third birthday.
* Type III (also 1-2 copies of L444P, possibly delayed by protective polymorphisms) occurs in [[Sweden|Swedish]] patients from the [[Norrbotten]] region. This group develops the disease somewhat later, but most die before their 30th birthday.

Diaz  ''et al'' suggest that the Gaucher-causing mutations entered the Ashkenazi Jewish gene pool in the early Middle Ages (48-55 generations ago).<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite journal |author=Diaz GA, Gelb BD, Risch N, ''et al'' |title=Gaucher disease: the origins of the Ashkenazi Jewish N370S and 84GG acid beta-glucosidase mutations |journal=Am. J. Hum. Genet. |volume=66 |issue=6 |pages=1821–32 |year=2000 |pmid=10777718|doi=10.1086/302946}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

<h level="2" i="6">==Epidemiology==</h>
* The National Gaucher Foundation states that around 1 in 100 people in the general U.S. population is a carrier for type 1 Gaucher's disease, giving a prevalence of 1 in 40,000: among [[Ashkenazi Jew]]s the rate of carriers is considerably higher, at roughly 1 in 15.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite web |url=http://www.gaucherdisease.org/prevalence.php |title=National Gaucher Foundation |accessdate=2007-05-30 |format= |work=}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>
* Type 2 Gaucher's disease shows no particular preference for any ethnic group.
* Type 3 Gaucher's disease is especially common in the population of the Northern Swedish region of [[Norrbotten]] where the incidence of the disease is 1 in 50,000.

<h level="2" i="7">==Treatment==</h>
For type 1 and most type 3 patients, [[enzyme replacement treatment]] with [[intravenous]] [[Recombinant DNA|recombinant]] glucocerebrosidase can dramatically decrease [[liver]] and [[spleen]] size, reduce skeletal abnormalities, and reverse other manifestations. The rarity of the disease means that dose-finding studies have been difficult to conduct, so there remains controversy over the optimal dose and dosing frequency.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Grabowski2008&quot;</attr></ext>  Due to the low incidence, this has become an [[orphan drug]] in many countries, meaning that a government recognizes and accomodates the financial constraints that limit research into drugs that address a small population. 

Successful [[bone marrow transplantation]] cures the non-neurological manifestations of the disease, because it introduces a [[monocyte]] population with active beta-glucosidase. However, this procedure carries significant risk and is rarely performed in Gaucher patients. Surgery to remove the spleen ([[splenectomy]]) may be required on rare occasions if the patient is anemic or when the enlarged organ affects the patient’s comfort. [[Blood transfusion]] may benefit some anemic patients. Other patients may require [[Replacement joint|joint replacement]] surgery to improve mobility and quality of life. Other treatment options include [[antibiotic]]s for [[infection]]s, [[antiepileptic]]s for seizures, bisphosphonates for bone lesions, and [[liver transplant]]s. Substrate reduction therapy may prove to be effective in stopping Type 2, as it can cross through the blood barrier into the brain. There is currently no effective treatment for the severe brain damage that may occur in patients with types 2 and 3 Gaucher disease. [[Gene therapy]] may be a future step.

Gaucher's disease has recently become a target for more than one effort at [[pharmacological chaperone|pharmacological chaperoning]], which involves the use of orally administered drugs that operate at a molecular level. 

The currently existing treatment of Gaucher's disease, Cerezyme ([[imiglucerase]] for injection), costs up to $550,000 annually for a single patient and the treatment should be continued for life. This recombinant beta-glucosidase is given intravenously. [[Miglustat]] is another drug approved for this disease in 2003.

<h level="2" i="8">==References==</h>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Reflist</title><part><name index="1"/><value>2</value></part></template>

<h level="2" i="9">== External links ==</h>
* <template><title>NINDS</title><part><name index="1"/><value>gauchers</value></part></template>
*[http://www.gaucher.org.uk/index.htm Gauchers News]
*[http://www.gaucher.org.uk/ega/alliance.htm European Gaucher Alliance]
*[http://www.gaucherdisease.org National Gaucher Foundation]

<template lineStart="1"><title>Lipid storage disorders</title></template>

[[Category:Hematology]]
[[Category:Lysosomal storage diseases]]
[[Category:Genetic disorders]]
[[Category:Autosomal recessive disorders]]
[[Category:Hepatology]]
[[Category:Rare diseases]]
[[Category:Ashkenazi Jews topics]]

[[de:Morbus Gaucher]]
[[es:Enfermedad de Gaucher]]
[[fr:Maladie de Gaucher]]
[[it:Malattia di Gaucher]]
[[he:מחלת גושה]]
[[nl:Ziekte van Gaucher]]
[[ja:ゴーシェ病]]
[[pl:Choroba Gauchera]]
[[pt:Doença de Gaucher]]
[[ru:Болезнь Гоше]]
[[sv:Gauchers sjukdom]]</root>