<root><template><title>Unreferenced</title><part><name>date</name><equals>=</equals><value>November 2007</value></part></template>
[[Image:Bidet Ego Kolo.jpg|thumb|222px|A [[toilet]] (left) and a bidet (right).]]
A '''bidet''' is a low-mounted [[plumbing fixture]] or type of [[sink]] intended for [[washing]] the [[genitalia]], inner [[buttocks]], and [[anus]]. Originally a [[French language|French]] word, in [[English language|English]] ''bidet'' is <template><title>pronEng</title><part><name index="1"/><value>bɪˈdei</value></part></template> ([[American English|US]]) or <template><title>IPA</title><part><name index="1"/><value>/ˈbiːdeɪ/</value></part></template> ([[British English|UK]]).

<h level="2" i="1">==History==</h>
[[Image:2008-02-02 Bidet.jpg|thumb|left|200px|An 18th century bidet in South Africa, with Chinese porcelain]]
[[Image:18th century bidet.jpg|thumb|right|290px|An 18th century etching of ladies 'mounted' on bidets]]
''Bidet'' is a [[French language|French]] word for [[pony]] (and in [[Old French]], ''bider'' meant ''to trot''). This [[etymology]] comes from the fact that one ''rides'' a bidet much like a pony is ridden.

The ''bidet'' appears to have been an invention of French [[furniture]] makers in the late 17th or early 18th century, although no exact date or [[inventor]] is known. Theories exist that its inventor is Christophe des Rosiers, furniture maker for the [[French royal family|French Royal Family]], but Marc-Antoine Jacoud is also rumored to have been the inventor. The earliest written reference to the bidet is in 1710. By 1900, due to [[plumbing]] improvements, the bidet (and [[chamber pot]]) moved from the [[bedroom]] to the bathroom. 1960 saw the introduction of the electronic bidet, an attachment which connects on to existing toilet arrangements &amp;mdash; ideal for bathrooms lacking the space for a separate bidet and toilet.

[[Image:Bidet top.jpg|thumb|right|250px|]]
Bidets are primarily used to [[hygiene|wash and clean]] the genitalia, [[perineum]], inner buttocks, and anus. They may also be used to clean any other part of the [[human body|body]]; they are very convenient for cleaning the feet, for example. Despite appearing similar to a [[toilet]], it would be more accurate to compare it to the [[washbasin]] or [[bathtub]]. In fact, the bidet is used by some for a baby bath<template><title>Who</title><part><name>date</name><equals>=</equals><value>April 2010</value></part></template>. Bidets once served as a practical way for couples to prepare themselves before sex, as well as to rinse themselves afterwards.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite web |url=http://www.hihut.com/bidet-culture-around-the-world-and-why-its-changing-in-america.html |title=Bidet Culture Around the World and Why It’s Changing in America! |accessdate=2009-12-13}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

Users who are unfamiliar with bidets often confuse a bidet with a [[urinal (restroom)|urinal]], toilet, or even a [[water fountain|drinking fountain]]. It is generally understood that the user should sit on a bidet facing the [[Tap (valve)|tap]] and nozzle for washing the genitalia, and should sit with back to the tap and wall when washing the anus and buttocks. For a thorough cleaning, the user should use a hand to scrub the area with soap after wetting, then rinse. A dedicated towel or wipe is often available for drying.

Bidets are made in several different [[design]]s. They may have one tap which pours (usually warm) water into a [[porcelain|china]] basin. The basin can be plugged and filled if necessary, or the water can be allowed to drain away. Other bidets have a [[nozzle]] which propels an arc of water up into the air. This jet of water is angled to easily reach the perianal and genital area.

[[Image:Bidet side.jpg|thumb|right|250px|A modern bidet]]

Bidets are common bathroom fixtures in many [[Southern Europe|southern European countries]] (especially [[Italy]], [[Spain]], [[Portugal]], [[Croatia]], [[Slovenia]] and [[Greece]]), some [[Americas|America]]n countries (especially [[Brazil]], [[Peru]], [[Cuba]], [[Paraguay]], [[Argentina]], [[Chile]] and [[Uruguay]]), some of [[Africa]] (especially [[Egypt]] and [[Morocco]]) and some parts of [[Asia]] (particularly in [[Japan]], [[India]], and [[South Korea]]). Almost all houses in the Arab world (including [[Lebanon]], [[Syria]], [[Jordan]], [[Kuwait]], [[Saudi Arabia]], [[Qatar]], and [[United Arab Emirates]]) are equipped with bidets. Although [[France]] is the country where the word ''bidet'' originated, not every house is equipped with one, especially the smaller or cheaper flats as well as recent constructions. Also almost all the houses in [[Argentina]]  [[Paraguay]] and  [[Uruguay]] are equipped with bidets. Although they do occasionally appear in North America or the UK, they are much less common there than in Continental Europe and Asia.

<h level="2" i="2">==Integration of toilet and bidet==</h>

A bidet may also be a nozzle attached to an existing toilet, or a part of the toilet itself. In this case, its use is restricted to cleaning the anus and genitals. Some bidets of this type have two nozzles, the shorter one, called the ''family nozzle'', is used for washing the area around the anus, and the longer one (''bidet nozzle'') is designed for women to wash their [[vulva]]e. These bidets are often controlled [[electronics|electronically]] rather than with a traditional tap, and some have an [[Electrical element|element]] under the seat which heats up to dry the user after washing. These bidet toilets have been popular in countries like [[India]] since British colonial days, as the use of just dry toilet paper to clean the perianal area is considered dirty and unhygienic there. The nozzle is sometimes controlled with an external tap within the reach of the hand. Traditionally, local style [[squatting toilet]]s have been more common in India and are more convenient to most Indians, especially of the lower income groups. But with the rise of westernization, western style pots have started becoming more common, and the most convenient way to wash the perianal area with these pots is simply to attach a bidet nozzle.

[[Image:SB-BidetIntegrated.jpg‎|thumb|right|250px|Toilet integrated bidet—simple bidet]]

In 1980 the first &quot;paperless toilet&quot; was launched in Japan, a combination toilet and bidet which also dries the user after washing. Combination toilet-bidets with seat warmers, or &quot;[[washlet]]s&quot;, are particularly popular in Japan and South Korea, found in approximately 60% of households. They are commonly found in [[hotel]]s and even some public facilities. These bidet-toilets, along with [[toilet seat]]/bidet units (to convert an existing toilet) are sold in many countries including the United States. For details see [[toilets in Japan]]. In Turkey, integrated bidet is standard in all toilets.

Bidet attachments are sometimes included on [[hospital]] toilets because of their utility in maintaining hygiene. In countries where the bidet is very common, prices are much lower. In [[Italy]], for example, the price for a bidet seldom exceeds €200 (about US$300), and it is not uncommon to find bidets priced as low as €40 (about US$60), especially in do-it-yourself stores. An alternative would be buying a bidet attachment for regular toilets. Many bidet retailers now offer toilet attachments that range from $79 to $650. 

In Middle Eastern countries, bidet attachments are much cheaper, being priced at around the equivalent of US$10–20, which is attributed to their popularity and availability.

Toilet seat bidet attachments are also becoming increasingly popular with the aging community. Many companies make bidet seat attachments that include remote controls to activate the water jets and air dryer. These conveniently placed remote controls may particularly benefit any individual with limited mobility.

The use of combined toilets/bidets with drying facility are becoming more widespread in the UK for use by disabled as this allows independent toileting for many, allowing greater independence and dignity. These are often special units with higher toilet bowls allowing easy wheelchair transfer, and which have some form of electronic remote control.

<h level="2" i="3">==See also==</h>
* [[Lota (vessel)]]
* [[Domestic water system]]
* [[Anal cleansing]]
* [[Washlet]]

<h level="2" i="4">== References ==</h>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Commons category</title><part><name index="1"/><value>Bidet</value></part></template>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Reflist</title></template>

<template lineStart="1"><title>Restrooms</title></template>

[[Category:Plumbing]]
[[Category:French inventions]]
[[Category:French words and phrases]]

[[cs:Bidet]]
[[de:Bidet]]
[[es:Bidé]]
[[eo:Bideo]]
[[fr:Bidet]]
[[gl:Bidé]]
[[io:Bideto]]
[[it:Bidet]]
[[he:בידה]]
[[hu:Bidé]]
[[nl:Bidet]]
[[ja:ビデ]]
[[no:Bidet]]
[[pl:Bidet]]
[[pt:Bidê]]
[[ru:Биде]]
[[sk:Bidet]]
[[sr:Биде]]
[[fi:Bidee]]
[[sv:Bidé]]
[[tr:Bide]]
[[uk:Біде]]
[[zh-yue:坐浴桶]]
[[zh:坐浴桶]]</root>