<root><template><title>Discrimination sidebar</title></template>
The '''disability rights movement''' aims to improve the [[quality of life]] of people with [[disability|disabilities]]. For people with physical disabilities [[accessibility]] and [[safety]] are primary issues that this movement works to reform.  Access to public areas such as city streets and public buildings and restrooms are some of the more visible changes brought about in recent decades.  A noticeable change in some parts of the world is the installation of [[elevator]]s, transit [[Elevator|lifts]], [[wheelchair ramp]]s and [[curb cut]]s, allowing people in [[wheelchair]]s and with other mobility impairments to use public sidewalks and [[public transit]] more easily and more safely.  These improvements have also been appreciated by parents pushing [[stroller]]s or [[carts]], [[bicycle]] users, and travelers with rolling luggage.  

Access to [[education]] and [[employment]] have also been a major focus of this movement.  [[Adaptive technology|Adaptive technologies]], enabling people to work jobs they could not have previously, help create access to jobs and economic [[independence]].  Access in the classroom has helped improve [[education]] opportunities and independence for people with disabilities.

The right to have an [[Independent Living|independent life]] as an adult, sometimes using paid assistant care instead of being [[institutionalisation|institutionalized]], is a major goal of this movement, and is the main goal of the similar [[independent living]] and [[self-advocacy]] movements, which are more strongly associated with people with [[intellectual disabilities]] and [[mental health]] disorders.  These movements have supported people with disabilities to live as more active participants in society.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Roberta Ann Johnson, &quot;Mobilizing the Disabled,&quot; in ''Social Movements of the Sixties and Seventies'', pp. 84-93</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

<h level="2" i="1">==History==</h>
In the [[United States]], the disability rights movement began in the 1970s,<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;'70s 250&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite book |title= How We Got Here: The '70s|last= Frum|first= David|authorlink= David Frum|coauthors= |year= 2000|publisher= Basic Books|location= New York, New York|isbn= 0465041957|page= |pages=250-251 |url= }}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> encouraged by the examples of the African-American [[American Civil Rights Movement (1955-1968)|civil rights]] and [[Second-wave feminism|women’s rights movement]]s, which began in the late 1960s. One of the most important developments was the growth of the [[Independent Living]] movement, which emerged in [[California]]. Another crucial turning point was the nationwide sit-in conceived by [[Frank Bowe]] and organized by the [[American Coalition of Citizens with Disabilities]] in 1977 of government buildings operated by [[HEW]] in [[San Francisco]]<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;'70s 250&quot;</attr></ext> and [[Washington DC]] that successfully led to the release of regulations pursuant to Section 504 of the Vocational [[Rehabilitation Act]] of 1973. Prior to the 1990 enactment of the [[Americans with Disabilities Act]], the [[Rehabilitation Act]] was the most important disability rights legislation in the United States.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Roberta Ann Johnson, &quot;Mobilizing the Disabled,&quot; p. 83-88</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> The Disability Rights and Education Defense Fund was begun in 1979.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;'70s 250&quot;</attr></ext>

In the UK, following extensive activism by disabled people over several decades, the [[Disability Discrimination Act 1995]] (DDA 1995) was passed. This makes it unlawful to discriminate david of their disabilities in relation to employment, the provision of goods and services, education and transport. It is a civil rights law. Other countries use constitutional, social rights or criminal law to make similar provisions. The Equality and Human Rights Commission provides support for the Act. Equivalent legislation exists in Northern Ireland, which is enforced by the Northern Ireland Equality Commission.

<h level="2" i="2">==Physical disabilities==</h>
[[Image:Disablemarker.jpg|thumb|left|250px|Floor marker for disabled people in Narita Airport, Japan]]
The focus of activists for the rights of people with physical disabilities began with access to public and private buildings and general accommodation of people who are less mobile or dextrous. In particular, they advocate the inclusion of wheelchair ramps, automatic doors, wide doors and corridors, and the elimination of unnecessary steps where ramps and elevators are not available.

While physical access remains an ongoing need,in the United States, other needs were raised and became elements in the ADA, [[Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990]] such as employment and transportation.

<h level="2" i="3">==Developmental disabilities==</h>
Advocates for the rights of people with [[developmental disabilities]] focus their efforts on gaining acceptance in the [[workforce]] and in everyday activities and events from which they might have been excluded in the past.

Unlike many of the leaders in the physical disability rights community, [[self-advocacy]] has been slow in developing for people with developmental disabilities. Public awareness of the civil rights movement for this population remains limited, and the stereotyping of people with developmental disabilities as non-contributing citizens who are dependent on others remains common.

<h level="2" i="4">==Personalities==</h>
* [[Ed Roberts (activist)|Ed Roberts]] is often referred to as the father of the disability right movements.  His efforts to get into college succeeded in his admission to UC Berkeley in 1962. His fight for access at Berkeley spread into seeking access in the community and the development of the first Center for Independent Living.  

*[[Judith Heumann]] co-founded the [[World Institute on Disability]] with Ed Roberts, and served as its co-director from 1983 to 1993.  She is now the [[World Bank Group]]'s advisor on disability and development.

* [[John Tyler (activist)|John Tyler]] was an advocate for the rights of the disabled who was himself disabled with severe polio. He parked his wheelchair in front of Metro buses in [[Seattle, Washington]], [[U.S.A.]] in the late 1970s and performed other actions to make sure that the proper wheelchair lifts, not the &quot;folding camel&quot; lifts, would be put onto the public transit buses. The original lifts could potentially dump people in wheelchairs, and also break down more easily. After his death from suicide on [[December 24]], [[1984]], he was remembered at [[Center Park]] in Seattle, Washington, the first apartment building built in the United States specifically for people in wheelchairs.

* [[Jeff Moyer]] is an important and unique musician to the Disability Rights Movement.  He began his work as the resident musician of the 504 protests in San Francisco, circa 1977. 

* [[Gabriela Brimmer]], a poet whose life was chronicled in the film ''[[Gaby -- A True Story]]'', overcame [[cerebral palsy]] to form a disability rights organization in her native [[Mexico]].

<h level="2" i="5">==Notes==</h>
<ext><name>references</name><attr> </attr></ext>

<h level="2" i="6">==References==</h>
*Roberta Ann Johnson, &quot;Mobilizing the Disabled,&quot; in ''Social Movements of the Sixties and Seventies'', edited by [[Jo Freeman]] (Longman, 1983), pp. 82-100; reprinted in ''Waves of Protest: Social Movements Since the Sixties'' edited by Jo Freeman and Victoria Johnson (Rowman and Littlefield, 1999), pp. 25-45.
*Paul K. Longmore and Laurie Umansky, editors, ''The New Disability History: American Perspectives'' (New York Univ. Press, 2001).
*Fred Pelka, ''The ABC Clio Companion to the Disability Rights Movement'' (ABC-Clio, 1997).
*Joseph P. Shapiro, ''No Pity: People with Disabilities Forging a New Civil Rights Movement'' (Times Books, 1993).  ISBN 0-8129-2412-6

<h level="2" i="7">==See also==</h>
* [[Inclusion (disability rights)]]
* [[Ableism]]
* [[Social model of disability]]
* [[Person Centred Planning]]
* [[List of disability rights activists]]
* [[List of disability rights organizations]]
* [[American Coalition of Citizens with Disabilities]]
* [[Architectural Barriers Act of 1968]]
* [[Americans with Disabilities Act]]
* [[Section 504]]
* [[Visitability]] - Social Integration Beyond Independent Living

<h level="2" i="8">==External links==</h>
* [http://www.uic.edu/orgs/sds Society for Disability Studies]
* [http://www.RollingRains.com The Rolling Rains Report on Travel, Disability, and Universal Design] A blog positioning inclusive consumer activities such as travel within the disability rights movement through the use of the movement's design philosophy [[Universal Design]].
* [http://www.einarhelander.com/ Disability Rights and Rehabilitation by Einar Helander] 

[[de:Behindertenbewegung]]
[[sr:Покрет за права особа са дисабилитетом]]

[[category:disability rights]]</root>