<root><template><title>distinguish</title><part><name index="1"/><value>anal plug</value></part></template>
<template lineStart="1"><title>refimprove</title><part><name>date</name><equals>=</equals><value>March 2012</value></part></template>
[[Image:Buttplug.png|thumb|right|Computer drawing of a blue buttplug.]]
A '''butt plug''' is a [[sex toy]] that is designed to be inserted into the [[rectum]] for [[sexual pleasure]].<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite book | first = Tristan | last = Taormino | authorlink = Tristan Taormino | year = 1997 | title =The Ultimate Guide to Anal Sex for Women| publisher = Cleis Press | isbn = 1-57344-028-0}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext><ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite web|url=http://www.likera.com/eq/plugs/diy-plug-1.php|title=Human anatomy and DIY plugs}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> In some ways, they are similar to a [[dildo]], but they tend to be shorter, and must have a flanged end to prevent the device from being lost inside the rectum.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite book|title=Anal Pleasure &amp; Health: A Guide for Men and Women|author=Jack Morin|year=2000|publisher=Down There Press|isbn=0-940208-20-2|page=96}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

<h level="2" i="1">==Basics==</h>
Unlike the [[vagina]], which is closed off by the [[cervix]], the [[rectum]] leads to the [[sigmoid colon]]. Objects that are inserted into the rectum can therefore potentially travel up into the [[bowel]]: the flared end on a butt plug exists to prevent this. Many dildos lack a flared end<template><title>Citation needed</title><part><name>date</name><equals>=</equals><value>December 2013</value></part></template>, and thus it is ill-advised to use such dildos anally since they may get stuck, requiring [[Rectal foreign body|medical extraction]].

In addition, the lower [[bowel]] above the [[rectum]] is easily perforated.<template><title>Citation needed</title><part><name>date</name><equals>=</equals><value>March 2009</value></part></template> For this reason, butt plugs tend to be shorter than dildos, and their marked size generally indicates the circumference of the device rather than the length. They must also be very smooth to avoid damaging the rectum or bowel. In order to get them into the rectum, they most commonly have a general profile of a round-ended cone which then narrows to a &quot;waist&quot; which locates itself at the anal sphincter, with the flared part outside the body, preventing the butt plug from slipping further into the body. The sphincter muscle will hold the plug in place by the waist, preventing the plug from slipping out unintentionally.

As with other activities involving anal penetration, such as [[anal sex]], large amounts of [[sexual lubricant]] and a slow gentle approach are needed to insert or remove a butt plug.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite book | author = Morin, Jack | title = Anal Pleasure and Health | edition = 3d | publisher = Down There Press | year = 1998 | isbn = 0-940208-20-2}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

Butt plugs are sometimes covered by [[condom]]s for hygiene and to allow for the easy disposal of any [[feces]] with which they may come into contact. Nevertheless, they should not be shared with other people, due to the risk of [[blood-borne disease]]s, including [[HIV]] that can arise from the transfer of body fluids from one person to another.

<h level="2" i="2">==Designs==</h>
[[Image:Zwei unterschiedliche Butt-Plugs.jpg|thumb|left|Two separate butt plugs.]]
Butt plugs come in a variety of colors, shapes, sizes, and textures. Some are designed to look like [[penis]]es, while some are ribbed or wavy. The majority, however, are shaped as shown in the picture above, having a thin tip which is wider in the middle, a notch to hold it in place once it is inserted, and a flared base to prevent complete insertion into the rectum. Some plugs are designed (long, flexible and curved) to penetrate the [[sigmoid colon]].

Butt plugs are made of a variety of materials, the most common being [[latex]]. Other materials used include [[silicone]], [[neoprene]], [[wood]], [[metal]], [[glass]], [[Rock (geology)|stone]], and many other materials. Silicone is a particularly good material, as it can be disinfected in boiling water.

There are butt plugs that &quot;ejaculate&quot; by squirting water or other viscous fluids into the rectum.
There are also vibrating butt plugs, and butt plugs that can inflate and expand.
Some butt plugs are specifically designed for men and [[Prostate massage|stimulate the prostate]]. Other butt plugs are manufactured with long hair or simulated animal tails attached to the base for use in [[human pony]] play or other animal fantasy role play.  Butt plugs are also now available that incorporate electro-stimulation.

Butt plugs can be moved in or out for pleasure; for this type of activity ribbed butt plugs can increase pleasure. They can also be worn continuously (or be lockable) for long periods of time.

Anal jewelry is a type of butt plug where the bulbous end is inserted into the anus and the end that remains outside of the body is decorated. Most anal jewelry pieces are made of [[stainless steel]] and typically have some kind of [[Gemstone|gem]] or ornate sculpture on the area that is to be worn outside of the body. These stainless steel pieces are also designed to be worn for an extended amount of time; although they provide a feeling of fullness in the [[anus]], they are more for show than for pleasure.

<h level="2" i="3">==Risks==</h>
<template lineStart="1"><title>see also2</title><part><name index="1"/><value>[[Prostate massage#Risks|Prostate massage risks]]</value></part></template>

The flange is not a foolproof method of preventing the plug from entering the rectum completely with subsequent inability to retrieve it. This is uncomfortable and may require medical intervention. Butt plugs of excess diameter can, especially when inserted too rapidly and/or too forcefully, lead to sphincter tear, detachment or other rectal failure. [[Kegel exercise]]s can help maintain normal, healthy sphincter function.

Generally for optimal pleasure, when inserting a butt-plug, one should exercise manipulative gentleness, progressive sizing and cautious patience.

While medical data is sparse it is not recommended to leave a butt plug inserted for longer than two to three hours.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>[http://thehealthybear.com/butt-plug-guide/ Butt Plug Safety Guide] accessed 20 October 2013</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

<h level="2" i="4">== Fetish plugs ==</h>
Fetish plugs are butt plugs that are designed in a way to be unusual, exciting, or unique in some way. A fetish plug is called such because it caters to male and female [[sexual fetish]]es.

One of the most common types of fetish plugs is the butt plug with faux animal tail.<template><title>Citation needed</title><part><name>date</name><equals>=</equals><value>March 2013</value></part></template> The animal tail, usually made with fake fur, is attached to the non-insertable end of the plug so that when worn or inserted, the impression is given that the wearer has an animal's tail. Some &quot;tail&quot; butt plugs popular in human puppy play are moulded from [[medical grade silicone]] allowing a simulated tail &quot;wag&quot;.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>[http://thehappypup.com/square-peg-puppy-tails/ Human Pup Play Tails] accessed 20 October 2013</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

<h level="2" i="5">==See also==</h>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Portal</title><part><name index="1"/><value>Sexuality</value></part></template>
* [[Anal beads]]
* [[Anal masturbation]]

<h level="2" i="6">==References==</h>
<template lineStart="1"><title>reflist</title></template>

<h level="2" i="7">==External links==</h>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Wiktionary</title><part><name index="1"/><value>butt plug</value></part></template>
* <template><title>Commons category-inline</title><part><name index="1"/><value>Butt plugs</value></part></template>

<template lineStart="1"><title>DEFAULTSORT:Butt plug</title></template>
[[Category:Anal eroticism]]
[[Category:Sex toys]]</root>