<root><template><title>Other uses</title><part><name index="1"/><value>Pegging (disambiguation)</value></part></template>
[[Image:Wiki-pegging.png|thumb|250px|alt=A naked man is on all fours. A naked woman is knelt behind him wearing a pink strap-on dildo. The woman is preparing to penetrate the man's anus with the dildo.|A woman pegging a man doggy-style with a [[Strap-on dildo|4-strap harness]] and [[dildo]].]]

'''Pegging''' is a sexual practice in which a woman penetrates a man's anus with a [[strap-on dildo]]. The [[neologism]] &quot;pegging&quot; was popularized when it became the winning entry in a contest in [[Dan Savage]]'s ''[[Savage Love]]'' sex advice column, held after an observation was made that there was no common name for the act.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=sl</attr><inner>These three links chronicle how the term ''pegging'' came into usage.
* [http://www.thestranger.com/seattle/SavageLove?oid=7446 Let's Vote], May 24, 2001
* [http://www.thestranger.com/seattle/SavageLove?oid=7576 Count Every Vote], June 7, 2001
* [http://www.thestranger.com/seattle/SavageLove?oid=7730 We Have a Winner!], June 21, 2001</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

<h level="2" i="1">==Pleasurable aspects==</h>
<h level="3" i="2">===Physical pleasure===</h>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Main</title><part><name index="1"/><value>Strap-on dildo</value></part></template>
In terms of physical pleasure, women may get direct stimulation from the base of the dildo, or in the case of a [[double-ended dildo]], from vaginal penetration.  A woman can use a secondary [[Vibrator (sensual)|vibrator]], between the dildo and her [[clitoris]], to get pleasure from pegging. Men may find stimulation of the anus, rectum, and adjacent organs, and particularly the [[prostate]], enjoyable, which can lead to an [[anal orgasm]].  Some men enjoy [[masturbation|masturbating]] (or being manually stimulated) during pegging.

<h level="3" i="3">===Psychological pleasure===</h>
Some people who engage in pegging may find pleasure in the psychological aspects of [[domination and submission]] which can be evoked through the practice. In particular, it is quite common for a [[femdom]] roleplay to culminate in a pegging. Given the stigma associated with anal sex (and its association with male homosexuality), some people, many of them [[heterosexual]], derive enjoyment from the associated [[taboo]].<template><title>Citation needed</title><part><name>date</name><equals>=</equals><value>September 2010</value></part></template>

Advice columnist Dan Savage wrote that he believes all men should try pegging at least once, as it may introduce them to a new enjoyable sexual activity and illuminate them to the receiver's perspective in sex.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=sl</attr></ext> A man may [[cross-dress]] in feminine [[lingerie]] such as [[stockings]], [[garters]] and high heeled shoes. This completion of the role reversal can be deeply erotic for some. Some people, particularly [[genderqueer]] people or those who engage in [[genderfuck]] may enjoy the [[gender]]-transgressive aspects of pegging. Some females may enjoy the feeling of having a &quot;simulated penis&quot;.

<h level="2" i="4">==Instructional materials==</h>
A few instructional movies and books have emerged in recent years, including ''[[Bend Over Boyfriend]]'', produced by Fatale Media, Inc., and directed by Shar Rednour, SIR Video co-founder.

The American pornographic film director and sex educator [[Tristan Taormino]] released an instructional pegging movie in 2009 by [[Vivid Entertainment]] Studio, ''Tristan Taormino's Expert Guide to Anal Pleasure for Men'',<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite journal | title=A Comparison of Male and Female Directors in Popular Pornography | first1=Chyng | last1=Sun | first2=Ana | last2=Bridges | first3=Robert | last3=Wosnitzer | first4=Erica | last4=Scharrer | first5=Rachael | last5=Liberman | url=http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1471-6402.2008.00439.x/full | doi=10.1111/j.1471-6402.2008.00439.x | journal=Psychology of Women Quarterly | volume=32 | issue=3 | pages=312–325 | month=September | year=2008 }}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> featuring a detailed explanation about male anal pleasure and strap-on dildo sex. In it, she teaches a workshop with instructions and skills for safe and pleasurable female on male anal sex. There are three scenes, in which pairs of pornographic actors explore different sexual devices and positions for pegging.

As an accomplished author of numerous sex guides and informational books on various sexual taboos, [[Violet Blue (author)|Violet Blue]] wrote and released ''The Adventurous Couple's Guide to Strap-On Sex'' in 2007.

<h level="2" i="5">==Pegging in pornography==</h>
Pegging has recently been featured in a number of [[pornographic movie]]s; the first pegging scene (long before the term was developed) appears to have been in the non-pornographic 1970 film ''[[Myra Breckinridge (film)|Myra Breckinridge]]'', based on the novel of the same name by [[Gore Vidal]], although it was not explicit. The first explicit such scene is believed to have occurred in the 1975 pornographic film ''[[The Opening of Misty Beethoven]]''.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=nault</attr><inner>{{cite journal | journal=[[Jump Cut (journal)|Jump Cut]] | number=52 | date=summer 2010 | title=Bend Over Boyfriend to Take it Like a Man: pegging pornography and the queer representation of straight sex | first=Curran | last=Nault | url=http://www.ejumpcut.org/currentissue/naultPegging/text.html }}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

In the 21st century, female-to-male strap-on pornography has suddenly become a flourishing industry in the U.S., with such a high market value that a number of studios have started producing dedicated series about it. The most notable titles are ''Strap It On'' (black women on white men), ''Babes Balling Boys'', which currently has sixteen editions, ''Strap Attack'', ''Strap-on Sirenz'', ''Strap-on Chicks'', ''Boss Bitches'', which currently has over two dozen editions, various movies produced by LEDA Studios, and San Francisco-based ''Men In Pain''. It is unclear what triggered the increasing popularity of this genre, but there are now several hundred exclusively pegging titles, as well as twice as many [[bisexual]] and straight films with strap-on scenes. Well-known female [[porn stars]] who have professed an enjoyment of pegging their male partners include [[Taylor Wane]], [[Brittany Andrews]], and [[Monique Covét]]. When questioned about her particular [[kink (sexual)|kink]] Covét replied, &quot;If we women have to take it from behind, then why not a man?&quot;<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>http://www.budapestsun.com/news/54577</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

<h level="2" i="6">==Examples from popular culture and the arts==</h>
*[[Dan Savage]] was the guest on ''[[The Colbert Report]]'' on November 29, 2010. During the interview Savage educated host [[Stephen Colbert]] on the practice of pegging.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{Cite video|title=Dan Savage - The Colbert Report|url=http://www.colbertnation.com/the-colbert-report-videos/366752/november-29-2010/dan-savage|accessdate=December 1, 2010|medium=Television production}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>
*There is a depiction of pegging in the [[William S. Burroughs]] novel ''[[Naked Lunch]]''.  The dildo used in the scene is called a Steely Dan III, and is the source from which the musical group [[Steely Dan]] takes its name.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite book | title=Steely Dan: Reelin' in the Years | first=Brian | last=Sweet | publisher=Omnibus Press | year=2000 | isbn=0711982791 | page=42 }}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext><ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>[http://www.steelydan.com/faq.html Official Steely Dan website FAQ]</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>
*Pegging was featured in the television show ''[[Weeds (TV series)|Weeds]]'', during the episode &quot;[[Crush Girl Love Panic]]&quot;, in a scene where [[Andy Botwin]], expecting to have sex with Yael Hoffman in her apartment, is surprised when she refuses to have vaginal sex with him, and dons a large strap-on.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=nault</attr></ext>
*A similar scene was featured in the UK comedy ''[[Peep Show (TV series)|Peep Show]]'' (2005). Jeremy and his girlfriend decide to act out each other's biggest fantasy. After having Jeremy's threesome, his girlfriend takes him to a bedroom. He does not know what she intends; she turns around and is wearing a large strap-on.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{Cite web|url=http://www.channel4.com/entertainment/tv/microsites/P/peep_show/series3_episode1.html|title=Episode One: Mugging (11 November 2005)|accessdate=2007-05-06|publisher=Channel 4}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>
*In the pilot episode of ''[[Dirt (TV series)|Dirt]]'' (2007), Lucy Spiller ([[Courtney Cox]]) blackmails Prince Tyreese ([[Rick Fox]]) with photographs of him being pegged by a prostitute.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=nault</attr></ext>
*In the film ''[[Zack and Miri Make a Porno]]'' (2008), Bubbles ([[Traci Lords]]) pegs Barry ([[Ricky Mabe]]).<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=nault</attr></ext>
*The theatre company ''Pack of Others'' have an entire theatrical performance devoted to &quot;spreading the word about the pleasures of prostate stimulation and strap-on sex.&quot;<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite web | url=http://www.packofothers.org/peg-ass-us | title=Peg-Ass-Us | accessdate=2011-01-09 }}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> The show has toured nationally and won Best Comedy at the 2008 [[fringe festival|San Francisco Fringe Festival]].<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>[http://www.theaterdogs.net/2008/09/23/fringe-felicitations-best-of-winners-encores-announced/ Fringe felicitations: Best of winners, encores announced]</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

<h level="2" i="7">==See also==</h>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Portal</title><part><name index="1"/><value>Sexuality</value></part></template>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Commons category</title><part><name index="1"/><value>Pegging</value></part></template>
* [[Anal sex]]
* [[Strap-on dildo]]

<h level="2" i="8">==References==</h>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Reflist</title></template>

<h level="2" i="9">==Further reading==</h>
* [[Violet Blue (author)|Violet Blue]]: ''The Adventurous Couple's Guide to Strap-On Sex'', Cleis Press, 2007, ISBN 157344278X
* [[Tristan Taormino]]: ''[[The Ultimate Guide to Anal Sex for Women]]'', (Cleis Press, 1997/2006) ISBN 1-57344-028-0

<template lineStart="1"><title>DEFAULTSORT:Pegging (Sexual Practice)</title></template>
[[Category:Anal eroticism]]
[[Category:BDSM]]
[[Category:Sexual acts]]

[[ca:Pegging]]
[[cs:Pegging]]
[[de:Pegging (Sexualpraktik)]]
[[gl:Pegging]]
[[it:Pegging]]
[[nl:Pegging]]
[[pl:Pegging]]
[[ru:Пеггинг]]
[[fi:Pegging]]
[[sv:Pegging]]
[[uk:Пеггінг]]</root>