<root><template><title>This</title><part><name index="1"/><value>the Star Trek franchise</value></part></template>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Infobox Media franchise
</title><part><name>head color</name><equals>=</equals><value>
</value></part><part><name>label color</name><equals>=</equals><value>
</value></part><part><name>title</name><equals>=</equals><value>''Star Trek''
</value></part><part><name>image</name><equals>=</equals><value>StarTrek Logo 2007.JPG
</value></part><part><name>imagesize</name><equals>=</equals><value>225
</value></part><part><name>image caption</name><equals>=</equals><value>The 2006 ''Star Trek 40th Anniversary'' franchise logo, featuring Captain Kirk ([[William Shatner]]) (left) and Mr. Spock ([[Leonard Nimoy]])
</value></part><part><name>creator</name><equals>=</equals><value>[[Gene Roddenberry]]
</value></part><part><name>origin</name><equals>=</equals><value>''[[Star Trek: The Original Series|Star Trek]]'' (1966)
</value></part><part><name>films</name><equals>=</equals><value>[[Star Trek: The Motion Picture]] (1979)&lt;br&gt;[[Star Trek II: The Wrath of Khan]] (1982)&lt;br&gt;[[Star Trek III: The Search for Spock]] (1984)&lt;br&gt;[[Star Trek IV: The Voyage Home]] (1986)&lt;br&gt;[[Star Trek V: The Final Frontier]] (1989)&lt;br&gt;[[Star Trek VI: The Undiscovered Country]] (1991)&lt;br&gt;[[Star Trek Generations]] (1994)&lt;br&gt;[[Star Trek: First Contact]] (1996)&lt;br&gt;[[Star Trek: Insurrection]] (1999)&lt;br&gt;[[Star Trek Nemesis]] (2002)&lt;br&gt;[[Star Trek (film)|Star Trek]] (2009)
</value></part><part><name index="1"/><value/></part><part><name>tv</name><equals>=</equals><value>[[Star Trek: The Original Series]] (1966–1969)&lt;br&gt;[[Star Trek: The Animated Series]] (1973–1974)&lt;br&gt;[[Star Trek: The Next Generation]] (1987–1994)&lt;br&gt;[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]] (1993–1999)&lt;br&gt;[[Star Trek: Voyager]] (1995–2001)&lt;br&gt;[[Star Trek: Enterprise]] (2001–2005)
</value></part></template>
<comment>&lt;!--editnote | NOTE: As prescribed in the Star Trek WikiProject, genre/generic references to Star Trek and the franchise should NOT be italicized, while references to the original series ARE. Formatting that is inconsistent with this will be corrected. For clarity: when making references to the original series, please endeavor to use the retronym ''Star Trek: The Original Series'' (''ST:TOS'', ''TOS'') instead. Thank you!--&gt;
</comment>
'''Star Trek''' is an American [[Science fiction on television|science fiction]] [[entertainment]] series.
The original ''[[Star Trek: The Original Series|Star Trek]]'' was an American television series, created by [[Gene Roddenberry]], which debuted in 1966 and ran for three seasons, following the interstellar adventures of [[James T. Kirk|Captain James T. Kirk]] and the crew of the Federation [[Starship Enterprise|Starship ''Enterprise'']]. These adventures were continued in an [[Star Trek: The Animated Series|animated television series]] and six feature films. Four more television series were produced, based in the same universe but following other characters: ''[[Star Trek: The Next Generation]]'', following the crew of a new Starship ''Enterprise'' set several decades after the original series; ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]]'' and ''[[Star Trek: Voyager]]'' set contemporaneously with ''The Next Generation''; and ''[[Star Trek: Enterprise]]'', set in the early days of human interstellar travel. Four additional feature films were produced, following the crew of ''The Next Generation'', and most recently [[Star Trek (film)|a 2009 movie reboot]] of the series featuring a young crew of the original ''Enterprise'' set in an alternate time line.

The franchise also includes dozens of computer and video games, hundreds of novels, as well as [[Star Trek: The Experience|a themed attraction]] in [[Las Vegas metropolitan area|Las Vegas]] (closed in September 2008). Beginning with the original television series and continuing with the subsequent films and series, the franchise has created a [[cult following|cult phenomenon]] and has spawned many [[pop culture]] references.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news | last =Italie| first =Hillel| title =Potter Reaches Cult Phenomenon Status| work =[[Seattle Times]]| publisher =[[Associated Press]]| date =2007-07-02| url =http://seattletimes.nwsource.com/html/entertainment/2003769419_webpotter02.html| accessdate =December 15 2008 }} In this article, the status of Star Trek as a cult phenomenon is repeatedly taken as read.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

<h level="2" i="1">==Conception and setting==</h>

As early as 1960, [[Gene Roddenberry]] had drafted a proposal for the science fiction series which would become ''Star Trek''. Although he publicly marketed it as a Western in outer space—a so-called &quot;[[Wagon Train]] to the Stars&quot;—he privately told friends that he was actually modeling it on [[Jonathan Swift]]'s ''[[Gulliver's Travels]]'', intending each episode to act on two levels: as a suspenseful adventure story and as a [[morality tale]].<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>See [[David Alexander (author)|David Alexander]], &quot;Star Trek Creator. The Authorized Biography of Gene Roddenberry&quot; and interview with Roddenberry in &quot;Something about the Author&quot; by Gale Research Company and chapter 11 of &quot;Trash Culture: Popular Culture and the Great Tradition&quot; by Richard Keller Simon</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

''Star Trek'' stories usually depict the adventures of humans and aliens who serve in the Federation's [[Starfleet]]. The protagonists are essentially [[altruism|altruists]] whose ideals are sometimes only imperfectly applied to the dilemmas presented in the series. The conflicts and political dimensions of ''Star Trek'' sometimes represent allegories for contemporary cultural realities: ''Star Trek: The Original Series'' addressed issues of the 1960s,<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite web| last =Snyder| first =J. William, Jr.| title =Star Trek: A Phenomenon and Social Statement on the 1960s| publisher =self-published| year =1995| url =http://www.ibiblio.org/jwsnyder/wisdom/trek.html| accessdate =December 15 2008}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> just as later spin-offs have reflected issues of their respective decades. Issues depicted in the various series include [[war]] and [[peace]], the value of personal loyalty, [[authoritarianism]], [[imperialism]], [[class warfare]], [[economics]], [[racism]], [[religion]], [[human rights]], [[sexism]] and [[feminism]], and the role of [[technology]].<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;smith57&quot;</attr><inner>Johnson-Smith, pp 57</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Roddenberry stated: &quot;[By creating] a new world with new rules, I could make statements about sex, religion, Vietnam, politics, and intercontinental missiles. Indeed, we did make them on ''Star Trek'': we were sending messages and fortunately they all got by the network.&quot;<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;smith79&quot;</attr><inner>Johnson-Smith, pp 79–85</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

Roddenberry intended the show to have a highly progressive political agenda reflective of the emerging counter-culture of the youth movement, though he was not fully forthcoming to the networks about this. He wanted Star Trek to show mankind what it might develop into, if only it would learn from the lessons of the past, most specifically by ending violence. An extreme example are the Vulcans, who had a very violent past but learned to control their emotions. His efforts were somewhat thwarted by the network's concerns over marketability. For example, they were opposed to Roddenberry's insistence on a racially diverse crew of the ''Enterprise'', against the opposition of the studio<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=whitfield</attr><inner>{{Cite book |last=Whitfield|first=Stephen PE |coauthors=Roddenberry, Gene |year=1968 |title=The Making of Star Trek|location=New York |publisher=Ballantine Books |oclc=23859}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>.

<h level="2" i="2">==Production history==</h>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Timeline of Star Trek franchise</title></template>
<h level="3" i="3">===Beginnings===</h>
In 1964 Roddenberry made a proposal for the original ''Star Trek'' TV series, to [[Desilu Studios]] as a &quot;''Wagon Train'' to the stars.&quot;<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite paper | last = Roddenberry | first = Gene | title = Star Trek is | version = First Draft | date = 1964-03-11 | url = http://www.ex-astris-scientia.org/misc/40_years/trek_pitch.pdf | format = PDF | accessdate = 2009-06-26}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> The  show's first pilot, &quot;[[The Cage (TOS episode)|The Cage]],&quot; starring Jeffrey Hunter as ''Enterprise'' Captain Chris Pike, was rejected by the network, however, Desilu executives were still impressed with the concept and made the unusual decision to commission a second pilot: &quot;[[Where No Man Has Gone Before]]&quot;.

The threat of cancellation loomed during the show's second season.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Herbert Solow and [[Robert H. Justman]], Inside Star Trek: The Real Story, Pocket Books, 1996, pp.377–394</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> The show's [[Fan (aficionado)|fanbase]] conducted an unprecedented letter-writing campaign, petitioning NBC to keep the show on the air.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Solow &amp; Justman, op. cit., pp.377–386</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> NBC renewed the show, but moved it from primetime to the &quot;[[Friday night death slot]]&quot;, and substantially reduced its budget.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Shatner, Star Trek Memories, pp.290–291</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Roddenberry reduced his direct involvement in ''Star Trek'' before the start of the season to protest the changed timeslot, and was replaced by [[Fred Freiberger]].

The series was canceled in its third season, despite the protests of a renewed letter writing campaign. Marketing personnel of the network complained to management that the series' cancellation was premature. New techniques for profiling demographics of the viewing audience later showed that Star Trek had been highly profitable for advertisers. The revelation came too late to resume production of the series.

<h level="3" i="4">===Rebirth===</h>
When the show was canceled, owner Paramount Studios hoped to recoup its production losses by selling the syndication rights to the show. The series went into reruns in the fall of 1972, and by the late 1970s had been sold in over 150 domestic and 60 international markets. The show developed a [[cult following]], and rumors of reviving the franchise began.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;sackett-15&quot;</attr><inner>Sackett &amp; Roddenberry, 15.</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

The first new ''Star Trek'' was ''[[Star Trek: The Animated Series]]''.  The series was produced by [[Filmation]] in association with [[Paramount Television]] and ran for two seasons from 1973 to 1974 on NBC, airing a total of twenty-two half-hour episodes.

The popularity of the syndicated ''Star Trek'' led [[Paramount Pictures]] and Roddenberry to begin developing a new ''[[Star Trek: Phase II]]'' series in May 1975.  Work on the series came to an end when the proposed Paramount Television Service folded.

Following the success of the science fiction movies ''[[Star Wars Episode IV: A New Hope|Star Wars]]'' and ''[[Close Encounters of the Third Kind]]'', the planned pilot episode of ''Phase II'' was adapted into the feature film, ''[[Star Trek: The Motion Picture]]''. The film was released in North America on December 7, 1979, with mixed reviews from critics. The film earned $139&amp;nbsp;million worldwide, which fell short of studio expectations but was enough for Paramount to propose a sequel. The studio forced Roddenberry to relinquish creative control of future sequels. In total, six Star Trek feature films were produced between 1979 and 1991.

In response to Star Trek's popularity in the movie theater, the series returned to the television in the critically acclaimed series ''[[Star Trek: The Next Generation]]'' (''TNG'') in 1987. The show was unusual in that it was broadcast as [[Broadcast syndication#First-run syndication in the U.S.|first-run syndication]] rather than on a major network. Paramount and the local stations split the advertising time.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite book|title=Star Trek Creator: The Authorized Biography of Gene Roddenberry|author=Alexander, David|publisher=Roc|year=1994|isbn=0-451-45440-5}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

<h level="3" i="5">===After Roddenberry===</h>

Star Trek's creator, Roddenberry, died on October 24, 1991, of heart failure at the age of 70. Roddenberry granted [[Rick Berman]], the executive producer of ''TNG'', control of the franchise. ''TNG'' had the highest ratings of any of the ''Star Trek'' series and was the #1 syndicated show during the last few years of its original seven-season run.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;TNG ratings&quot;</attr><inner> [http://www.ee.surrey.ac.uk/Contrib/SciFi/StarTrek/history.html Star Trek&amp;nbsp;— A Short History] URL accessed August 21, 2006</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

In response to ''TNG's'' success, Paramount began production of a [[Spin-off (media)|spin-off]] ''Star Trek'' series ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|Deep Space Nine]]'', which was released in 1993. While never as popular as ''TNG'', ''DS9'' had solid ratings, and it also lasted seven seasons. 

In January 1995, a few months after ''TNG'' ended, a fourth TV series, ''[[Star Trek: Voyager|Voyager]]'' was released. Viewer interest in ''Star Trek'' peaked in the mid-1990s with ''DS9'' and ''Voyager'' airing concurrently and three of the four ''TNG''-based feature films being released in 1994, 1996 and 1998.  ''Voyager'' was the flagship show of the new [[UPN|United Paramount Network]] (UPN) and thus, the first ''Star Trek'' series since the original that was shown on a major network.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Voyagerflagship&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite news| last = Levesque| first =  John| title = UPN in Search of Post-'Voyager' Flagship| publisher = Seattle PI| date = 2001-01-06| url = http://www.seattlepi.com/tv/upn06.shtml| accessdate = 2009-06-30}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> The show lasted seven seasons until 2001, making it the longest running show in UPN's short history. 

A new prequel ''Star Trek'' TV series, ''[[Star Trek: Enterprise|Enterprise]]'', set before the ''TOS'', was produced after ''Voyager'' ended.  Enterprise did not enjoy the high ratings of its predecessors and by the series' third season, UPN threatened to cancel ''Enterprise''. Fans launched a campaign reminiscent of the one that saved the third season of the ''Original Series''. Paramount reacted to the fan requests the same way it did for ''TOS'' by renewing ''Enterprise'' for a fourth season,<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;entrenew&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite web | title = Fan Groups, Sites Rally on Behalf of ''Enterprise'' | publisher = startrek.com| date = 2004-05-28| url=http://www.startrek.com/startrek/view/news/article/5500.html| accessdate = 2009-07-04}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> but moving it to the &quot;Friday night death slot&quot;.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;entrenew2&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite press release| title = UPN's 2004-2005 Schedule| publisher = UPN| date = 2004-05-20| url = http://www.startrek.com/startrek/view/news/article/5500.html| accessdate = 2009-07-04}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Like the ''Original Series'', ''Enterprise'' did not fare well during this time slot.  UPN announced the cancellation of ''Enterprise'' at the end of its fourth season, and its final episode aired on May 13, 2005.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite web |title=Star Trek: Enterprise Canceled! |date=2005-02-03 |work=Startrek.com |url=http://www.startrek.com/startrek/view/news/article/9469.html |accessdate=2007-12-18 }}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Fan groups, such as &quot;Save Enterprise&quot;, again attempted to save the series<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=TrekUnited</attr><inner>{{cite web |title=Save Enterprise 2005 Outlook |work=TrekUnited.com |url=http://www.trekunited.com/news/content/view/21/44/1/1/ |accessdate=2007-12-18 }}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> and even announced a drive to raise $30&amp;nbsp;million to privately finance a fifth season of ''Enterprise''.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=TrekUnited</attr></ext> Though the effort garnered considerable press, the fan drive was unsuccessful in saving the series. The cancellation of ''Enterprise'' ended an eighteen-year production run of ''Star Trek'' programming on television. This, along with the poor box office performance in 2002 of the film ''[[Star Trek Nemesis|Nemesis]]'', cast an uncertain light upon the future of the ''Star Trek'' franchise in general.

Berman, who had been responsible for many of the franchise's commercial successes, was relieved of control of the Star Trek franchise upon the cancellation of ''Enterprise''.

<h level="3" i="6">===Reboot===</h>
In 2007, Paramount hired a new creative team to [[Reboot (fiction)|reboot]] the franchise. Writers [[Roberto Orci]] and [[Alex Kurtzman]], and ''[[Lost (series)|Lost]]'' producer, [[J. J. Abrams]], were given the freedom to reinvent the feel of Trek and alter the canonical timeline.

An eleventh film, titled ''[[Star Trek (film)|Star Trek]]'', was released in May 2009. The eleventh ''Star Trek'' film's marketing campaign targeted non-fans, even using the phrase &quot;this is not your father's ''Star Trek''&quot; in the film's advertisements.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;NotFather&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite news | last = Adler| first = Margot| title = Some Older 'Star Trek' Fans May Skip This Voyage| publisher = NPR| date = 2009-05-06| url = http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=103824300| accessdate = 2009-07-04}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

The film has earned considerable critical and financial success, grossing the most of any ''Star Trek'' film, even in inflation-adjusted dollars.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;BoxofficeXI&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite web|url=http://www.airlockalpha.com/node/6469|title='Star Trek' Becomes Highest Grossing Franchise Film|last=Hinman|first=Michael|date=2009-06-23|publisher=Airlock Alpha|accessdate=2009-08-03}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> The film's major cast members have signed on for two sequels.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news | author = Pascale, Anthony | title = Paramount Already Thinking About Sequel To Abrams Star Trek | publisher = TrekMovie | date = 2008-04-06 | url = http://trekmovie.com/2008/06/04/paramount-already-thinking-about-sequel-to-abrams-star-trek/ | accessdate=2008-06-05}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> The script for the twelfth film is projected for completion around December 2009, with the film's release scheduled for mid-2011 coinciding with the 45th anniversary of Star Trek.

Abrams' was not the first team to propose a reboot. An attempt was also made by [[J. Michael Straczynski]] and [[Bryce Zabel]] to reboot the franchise with the crew of the original series, but Paramount ignored the proposal as they were not &quot;even willing to talk about ''Star Trek''&quot;.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite news|author=Neuman, Clayton|title=Masters of SciFi&amp;nbsp;— J. Michael Straczynski on Changeling's Message and Warp-Speed Writing for Ninja Assassin|work=[[AMC (TV network)|AMC]]|date=2008-10-13|url=http://blogs.amctv.com/scifi-scanner/2008/10/interview-with-j-michael-straczynski-2.php|accessdate=2008-10-14}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext><ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite web|author=J. Michael Straczynski, [[Bryce Zabel]]|title=''Star Trek'': Reboot the Universe|url=http://bztv.typepad.com/newsviews/files/ST2004Reboot.pdf|format=PDF|accessdate=2008-10-14}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

<h level="3" i="7">===Franchise ownership===</h>
The original series began production under [[Desilu Productions]]. With the merger of Desilu into Paramount Pictures, that studio assumed outright ownership of the ''Star Trek'' franchise until 2006, when [[CBS]] took over ownership of the franchise. Certain aspects (feature film and DVD distribution rights) are still owned by Paramount.

<h level="2" i="8">==Television series==</h>
The core of the ''Star Trek'' franchise is six television series: ''The Original Series'', ''The Animated Series'', ''The Next Generation'', ''Deep Space Nine'', ''Voyager'', and ''Enterprise''.  In total [[List of Star Trek episodes|726&amp;nbsp;''Star Trek'' episodes]] have been produced across the 30&amp;nbsp;seasons of the TV series.

<h level="3" i="9">===''The Original Series'' (1966–1969)===</h>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Main</title><part><name index="1"/><value>Star Trek: The Original Series</value></part></template>
''Star Trek'', also known as &quot;''TOS''&quot; or The Original Series, debuted in the United States on NBC on September 8, 1966.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;TOS debut&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite news | last =Lee| first =Luaine| title ='Star Trek' turns 40| work =[[San Jose Mercury News]]| publisher =[[McClatchy News]]| date =August 18 2006| url =http://www.mercurynews.com/mld/mercurynews/entertainment/15305203.htm| archiveurl =http://web.archive.org/web/20060901115942/http://www.mercurynews.com/mld/mercurynews/entertainment/15305203.htm| archivedate = September 1 2006| accessdate =December 15 2008 }}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> The show tells the tale of the crew of the [[starship]] ''[[USS Enterprise (NCC-1701)|Enterprise]]'' and its five-year mission &quot;to boldly go [[where no man has gone before]].&quot; The original 1966–69 television series featured  [[William Shatner]] as Captain [[James T. Kirk]], [[Leonard Nimoy]] as [[Spock]], [[DeForest Kelley]] as [[Dr. Leonard McCoy|Dr. Leonard &quot;Bones&quot; McCoy]], [[James Doohan]] as [[Montgomery Scott|Montgomery &quot;Scotty&quot; Scott]], [[Nichelle Nichols]] as [[Uhura]], [[George Takei]] as [[Hikaru Sulu]], and [[Walter Koenig]] as [[Pavel Chekov]]. During its original run, it was nominated several times for the [[Hugo Award for Best Dramatic Presentation]] and won twice: for the two-parter &quot;[[The Menagerie (Star Trek)|The Menagerie]]&quot; and the [[Harlan Ellison]]-written episode &quot;[[The City on the Edge of Forever]]&quot;. After three seasons the show was canceled and the last original episode aired on June 3, 1969.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;TOS end&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite web| title =Star Trek: Summary| work =[[TV.com]]| url =http://www.tv.com/star-trek/show/633/summary.html| accessdate =December 15 2008}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>. It was, however, highly popular with science-fiction fans and engineering students, in spite of generally low [[Nielsen ratings]]. The series subsequently became [[Cultural influence of Star Trek|popular]] in reruns and a cult following developed, complete with fan conventions.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;TOS debut&quot;</attr></ext> Originally presented under the title ''Star Trek'', it has in recent years become known as ''Star Trek: The Original Series'' or as &quot;Classic Star Trek&quot;—[[retronym]]s that distinguish it from its sequels and the franchise as a whole.

<h level="3" i="10">===''The Animated Series'' (1973–1974)===</h>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Main</title><part><name index="1"/><value>Star Trek: The Animated Series</value></part></template>
''Star Trek: The Animated Series'' was produced by Filmation and ran for two seasons from 1973 to 1974. Most of the original cast performed the voices of their characters from ''The Original Series'', and many of the original series' writers, such as [[D. C. Fontana]], [[David Gerrold]] and [[Paul Schneider (writer)|Paul Schneider]], wrote for the series. While the animated format allowed the producers to create more exotic alien landscapes and lifeforms, the liberal reuse of shots and musical cues as well as animation errors have tarnished the series' reputation.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite web| last =Dursin| first =Andre| title =Filmation's Star Trek Beams Up: Andy Reviews The Animated Adventures| work =The Aisle Seat| date =November 14 2006| url =http://www.andyfilm.com/11-14-06.html| accessdate =December 15 2008}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Although it was originally sanctioned by Paramount, which became the owner of the ''Star Trek'' franchise following its acquisition of [[Desilu]] in 1967, Roddenberry forced Paramount to stop considering the series [[Canon (Star Trek)|canonical]]<template><title>Citation needed</title><part><name>date</name><equals>=</equals><value>September 2009</value></part></template>. Even so, elements of the animated series have been used by writers in later live-action series and movies. As of June 2007, the Animated Series is once again part of the official canon, as confirmed by the official website, Startrek.com.

''TAS'' won ''Star Trek's'' first [[Emmy Award]] on May 15, 1975.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0069637/awards IMDB]</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> ''Star Trek TAS'' briefly returned to television in the mid-1980s on the children's cable network [[Nickelodeon (TV Channel)|Nickelodeon]]. Nickelodeon's Evan McGuire greatly admired the show and used its various creative components as inspiration for his short series called ''Piggly Wiggly Hears A Sound'' which never aired. Nickelodeon parent [[Viacom]] would purchase Paramount in 1994. In the early 1990s, the [[Sci Fi Channel (United States)|Sci-Fi Channel]] also began rerunning TAS. The complete TAS was also released on [[Laserdisc]] format during the 1980s.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;TAS&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite web| title =Star Trek Animated&amp;nbsp;— The animated series| work =ScienceFictionBuzz.com| url =http://www.sciencefictionbuzz.com/startrekanimated.html| accessdate =December 15 2008}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> The complete series was first released in the USA on eleven volumes of [[VHS]] tapes in 1989. All 22 episodes were released on [[DVD]] in 2006.

<h level="3" i="11">===''The Next Generation'' (1987–1994)===</h>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Main</title><part><name index="1"/><value>Star Trek: The Next Generation</value></part></template>
''Star Trek: The Next Generation'', also known as &quot;''TNG''&quot;, is set approximately a century after The Original Series (2364-2370). It features a new starship, the [[USS Enterprise (NCC-1701-D)|''Enterprise''-D]], and a new crew led by Captain [[Jean-Luc Picard]] ([[Patrick Stewart]]) and Commander [[William Riker]] ([[Jonathan Frakes]]). The series introduced alien races new to the Federation as crew members, including [[Deanna Troi]], a half-[[Betazoid]] counselor played  by [[Marina Sirtis]], and [[Worf]] as the first [[Klingon]] officer in Starfleet, played by [[Michael Dorn]]. It also featured [[Gates McFadden]] as Dr. [[Beverly Crusher]], [[LeVar Burton]] as chief engineer [[Geordi La Forge]], and the android [[Data (Star Trek)|Data]] portrayed by [[Brent Spiner]]. The show premiered on September 28, 1987, and ran for seven seasons, ending on May 23, 1994.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;TNG series&quot;</attr><inner>[http://www.tv.com/star-trek-the-next-generation/show/137/summary.html Star Trek: The Next Generation TV Show] URL accessed August 21, 2006</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Unlike the previous television outings, the program was [[Broadcast syndication|syndicated]] instead of airing on network television. It had the highest ratings of any of the ''Star Trek'' series and was the #1 syndicated show during the last few years of its original run, allowing it to act as a springboard for ideas in other series. Many relationships and races introduced in ''TNG'' became the basis of episodes in ''Deep Space 9'' and ''Voyager''.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;TNG ratings&quot;</attr></ext> It was nominated for an [[Emmy]] for Best Dramatic Series during its final season. It also received a [[Peabody Award]] for Outstanding Television Programming for the episode &quot;[[The Big Goodbye]]&quot;.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;TNG Emmy&quot;</attr><inner>[http://www.bbc.co.uk/cult/st/tng/intro.shtml BBC Online&amp;nbsp;— Star Trek: The Next Generation] URL accessed August 21, 2006</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

<h level="3" i="12">===''Deep Space Nine'' (1993–1999)===</h>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Main</title><part><name index="1"/><value>Star Trek: Deep Space Nine</value></part></template>
''Star Trek: Deep Space Nine'', also known as &quot;DS9&quot;, is set during the last years and the immediate post-years of ''The Next Generation'' (2369-2375) and was in production for seven seasons, debuting the week of January 3, 1993.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;DS9 series&quot;</attr><inner>[http://www.tv.com/star-trek-deep-space-nine/show/166/summary.html Star Trek: Deep Space Nine TV Show] URL accessed August 21, 2006</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Like ''Star Trek: The Next Generation'', it aired in syndication in the United States and Canada. It is the only ''Star Trek'' series to take place primarily on a space station rather than aboard a starship. It is set on the [[Cardassian]]-built [[space station]] [[Deep Space Nine (space station)|Deep Space Nine]], located near the planet [[Bajor]] and a uniquely stable [[wormhole]] that provides immediate access to the distant [[Galactic quadrants (Star Trek)#Gamma Quadrant|Gamma Quadrant]].<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Emissary&quot;</attr><inner>[http://www.startrek.com/startrek/view/series/DS9/episode/68084.html STARTREK.COM: Emissary]. URL accessed August 21, 2006</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> The show chronicles the events of the station's crew, led by Commander (later Captain) [[Benjamin Lafayette Sisko|Benjamin Sisko]], played by [[Avery Brooks]], and Major (later Colonel) [[Kira Nerys]], played by [[Nana Visitor]]. Recurring plot elements include the repercussions of the lengthy and brutal [[Cardassian Occupation]] of Bajor, Sisko's spiritual role for the [[Bajoran]]s as the Emissary of the [[Prophet (Star Trek)|Prophets]] and in later seasons a war with the [[Dominion (Star Trek)|Dominion]]. ''Deep Space Nine'' stands apart from earlier Trek series for its lengthy serialized storytelling, conflict within the crew, and religious themes—all of which were elements that were praised by critics and audiences but that Roddenberry had forbidden in the original series and ''The Next Generation''.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite web |url=http://web.archive.org/web/20030407175159/http://scifi.about.com/blinterarma2.htm |title=Review of &quot;Inter Arma Enim Silent Leges&quot; |accessdate=2006-10-29 }}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Nevertheless, he was made aware of plans to make ''DS9'' before his death, so this was the last ''Star Trek'' series with which he was connected.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite web|url=http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0106145/trivia|title=Trivia for Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|publisher=IMDB|accessdate=2007-10-14}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

<h level="3" i="13">===''Voyager'' (1995–2001)===</h>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Main</title><part><name index="1"/><value>Star Trek: Voyager</value></part></template>
''Star Trek: Voyager'' was produced for seven seasons, airing from January 16, 1995, to May 23, 2001, launching a new Paramount-owned television network UPN. It features [[Kate Mulgrew]] as Captain [[Kathryn Janeway]],<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;VOY woman&quot;</attr><inner>[http://www.revolutionsf.com/article.html?id=131 RevolutionSF&amp;nbsp;— Star Trek: Voyager : Review] URL accessed August 24, 2006</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> the first female commanding officer in a leading role of a ''Star Trek'' series, and Commander [[Chakotay]], played by [[Robert Beltran]]. ''Voyager'' takes place at about the same time as ''Deep Space Nine'' and the years following that shows end (2371-2378). The premiere episode has the [[USS Voyager (Star Trek)|USS ''Voyager'']] and its crew pursue a [[Maquis (Star Trek)|Maquis]] ship (crewed by Federation rebels). Both ships become stranded in the [[Delta Quadrant]] about 75,000 [[light year]]s from Earth.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;VOY LY&quot;</attr><inner>[http://www.fandango.com/startrek:voyager%5Btvseries%5D_v263074/summary] Star Trek: Voyager TV series&amp;#93; synopsis URL accessed April 4, 2007</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Faced with a 75-year voyage to Earth, the crew must learn to work together and overcome challenges on the long and perilous journey home while also seeking ingenious ways to shorten the return voyage. Like ''Deep Space Nine'', early seasons of ''Voyager'' feature greater conflict between its crew members than is seen in later shows. Such conflict often arises from friction between &quot;by-the-book&quot; Starfleet crew and rebellious Maquis fugitives forced by circumstance to work together on the same ship. Eventually, though, they settle their differences, after which the overall tone becomes more reminiscent of ''The Original Series''. ''Voyager'' is originally isolated from many of the familiar aspects and races of the ''Star Trek'' franchise, barring those few represented on the crew. This allowed for the creation of new races and original plot lines within the series. Later seasons, however, brought an influx of characters and races from prior shows, such as the [[Borg (Star Trek)|Borg]], [[Q (Star Trek)|Q]], the [[Ferengi]], [[Romulan]]s, [[Klingon]]s, [[Cardassian]]s as well as cast members of ''The Next Generation''.

<h level="3" i="14">===''Enterprise'' (2001–2005)===</h>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Main</title><part><name index="1"/><value>Star Trek: Enterprise</value></part></template>
''Star Trek: Enterprise'', originally titled ''Enterprise'', produced for an abbreviated four seasons airing from September 26, 2001, to May 13, 2005, is a prequel to the other ''Star Trek'' series,<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;ENT prequel&quot;</attr><inner>[http://www.starpulse.com/Television/Star_Trek:_Enterprise/Summary/ Star Trek: Enterprise Summary] URL accessed August 24, 2006</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> taking place in the 2150s, some 90&amp;nbsp;years after Zefram Cochrane developed the first warp-capable starship from a ballistic missile and about a decade before the founding of the Federation. The series shows how the first extraterrestrial contact with the Vulcans and subsequent guidance led to Earth's first warp-five capable starship, the ''[[Enterprise (NX-01)|Enterprise]]'', commanded by Captain [[Jonathan Archer]] played by [[Scott Bakula]], and Commander [[T'Pol]], played by [[Jolene Blalock]]. For the first two seasons, ''Enterprise'' is mostly episodic, like ''The Original Series'', ''The Next Generation'' and ''Voyager''. The third season's &quot;[[Xindi (Star Trek)|Xindi mission]]&quot; arc carried through the entire season. Season&amp;nbsp;4 was especially known for showing the origins of several common elements in the other series, due to the producers having recruited as writers Trek experts Mike Sussman and the writing team of [[Judith and Garfield Reeves-Stevens]]. In addition, season&amp;nbsp;4 rectified and resolved some core continuity problems in the series (some of which were created in season 1 of ''Enterprise''), most notably the decades-old issue of the drastic change in the appearance of the Klingons between ''TOS'' and other ''Trek'' series. The fourth season's story arcs are often spread to two or three episodes. Ratings for ''Enterprise'' started strong but declined rapidly, although longtime viewers were pleased by the final season's many homages to other ''Trek'' series.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner> This is noted in the review of the last season at DVDVerdict {{cite news|title=DVD Verdict Review Star Trek:Enterprise Season Four| url=http://www.dvdverdict.com/reviews/enterpriseseason4.php}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

<h level="2" i="15">==Feature films==</h>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Main</title><part><name index="1"/><value>Star Trek (film series)</value></part></template>
Paramount Pictures has produced eleven ''Star Trek'' feature films, the most recent released in May 2009 with a twelfth in development, possibly to be released in 2011, which will celebrate the ''Star Trek'' franchise's forty-fifth anniversary. The first six films continue the adventures of the ''The Original Series'' cast; the seventh, ''Generations'' was designed as a transition from that cast to ''The Next Generation''; the next three, 8–10, were exclusively ''Next Generation''. Although North American and UK releases of the films were no longer numbered following the sixth film, European releases continued numbering the films up until ''Nemesis''. The eleventh film, titled ''Star Trek'', is a prequel/reboot of ''TOS'' set prior to James T. Kirk's graduation from [[Starfleet Academy]], and promotion to the rank of Captain. A twelfth film is currently in its early stages of production.

{|class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;font-size:97%; text-align:left;&quot;
|-
!Title
!Release date
|-
|''[[Star Trek: The Motion Picture]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot;| December 7, 1979
|-
|''[[Star Trek II: The Wrath of Khan|The Wrath of Khan]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot;| June 4, 1982
|-
|''[[Star Trek III: The Search for Spock|The Search for Spock]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot;| June 1, 1984
|-
|''[[Star Trek IV: The Voyage Home|The Voyage Home]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot;| November 26, 1986
|-
|''[[Star Trek V: The Final Frontier|The Final Frontier]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot;| June 9, 1989
|-
|''[[Star Trek VI: The Undiscovered Country|The Undiscovered Country]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot;| December 6, 1991
|-
|''[[Star Trek Generations|Generations]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot;| November 18, 1994
|-
|''[[Star Trek: First Contact|First Contact]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot;| November 22, 1996
|-
|''[[Star Trek: Insurrection|Insurrection]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot;| December 11, 1998
|-
|''[[Star Trek Nemesis|Nemesis]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot;| December 13, 2002
|-
|''[[Star Trek (film)|Star Trek]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot;| May 8, 2009
|-
|Untitled 12th movie
|align=&quot;center&quot;| TBA
|}

<h level="2" i="16">==Spin-off media==</h>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Main</title><part><name index="1"/><value>Star Trek spin-off fiction</value></part></template>
The ''Star Trek'' franchise has a large number of novels, comic books, video games, and other materials, which are generally considered [[canon (Star Trek)|non-canon]].

<h level="3" i="17">===Books===</h>
<template lineStart="1"><title>See also</title><part><name index="1"/><value>List of Star Trek novels</value></part></template>
Since 1967, hundreds of original novels, short stories, and television and movie adaptations have been published. The very first original ''Star Trek'' novel to be published was ''[[Mission to Horatius]]'' by [[Mack Reynolds]], which was published in hardcover by [[Whitman Books]] in 1968.

The first publisher of ''Star Trek'' fiction aimed at adult readers was [[Bantam Books]]. In 1970, James Blish wrote the first original ''Star Trek'' novel published by Bantam, ''[[Spock Must Die!]]''.  [[Pocket Books]] is currently the publisher of ''Star Trek'' novels.

Prolific ''Star Trek'' novelists include [[Peter David]], [[Diane Carey]], [[Keith R.A. DeCandido]], [[J.M. Dillard]], [[Diane Duane]], [[Michael Jan Friedman]], and [[Judith and Garfield Reeves-Stevens]]. Several actors and writers from the television series have written books: William Shatner, and [[John de Lancie]], [[Andrew J. Robinson]], [[J. G. Hertzler]], and [[Armin Shimerman]] have written or co-written books featuring their respective characters. ''Voyager'' producer [[Jeri Taylor]] wrote two novels featuring backstory for ''Voyager'' characters, and screen authors [[David Gerrold]], [[D. C. Fontana]], and [[Melinda M. Snodgrass|Melinda Snodgrass]] have also penned books.

<h level="3" i="18">===Comics===</h>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Main</title><part><name index="1"/><value>Star Trek comics</value></part></template>
''Star Trek''-based comics have been published by a number of companies almost continuously since 1967. Publishers include [[Marvel Comics|Marvel]], [[DC Comics|DC]], [[Malibu Comics|Malibu]], [[Wildstorm]], and [[Gold Key]]. [[Tokyopop]] currently is publishing an anthology of ''Next Generation''-based stories presented in the style of [[Japan]]ese [[manga]].<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite web |title='Star Trek: The Next Generation' Goes Manga, But Will Picard Lose The Captain's Chair? |author=Marshall, Rick |date=4 April 2009 |publisher= [[MTV|MTV Splash Page]] |url=http://splashpage.mtv.com/2009/04/14/star-trek-the-next-generation-goes-manga-but-will-picard-lose-the-captains-chair/ |accessdate=4 January 2010}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> As of 2006, [[IDW Publishing]] secured publishing rights to ''Star Trek'' comics<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite press release |url=http://www.idwpublishing.com/titles/startrek.shtml/ |title=Star Trek Comics Soar Again |date=November 9, 2006 |accessdate=2006-12-25 |publisher=[[IDW Publishing]]}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> and published a [[prequel]] to the 2009 film, ''[[Star Trek: Countdown]]''.

<h level="3" i="19">===Games===</h>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Main</title><part><name index="1"/><value>Star Trek games</value></part></template>
The ''Star Trek'' franchise also has numerous games in many different formats. Beginning in 1967 with a [[board game]] based on the original series and continuing through 2009 with online and DVD games, ''Star Trek'' games continue to be popular among fans. The most recent video games of the series are ''[[Star Trek: Legacy]]'' and ''[[Star Trek: Conquest]]''. An MMORPG based on ''Star Trek'' called ''[[Star Trek Online]]'' is being developed by [[Cryptic Studios]] and will be published by [[Atari]]. It is set in the TNG universe and not the re-imagined Universe portrayed in JJ Abrams' ''Star Trek'', although it will take into account the events portrayed at the start of the film and in the prequel comics. The game is currently in the first round of Closed Beta Testing, and Cryptic recently confirmed that its release date has been set to February 2, 2010.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>[http://www.startrekonline.com/faq#4 Cryptic's Star Trek Online MMORPG&amp;nbsp;— FAQ]</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

<h level="2" i="20">==Cultural impact==</h>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Main</title><part><name index="1"/><value>Cultural influence of Star Trek</value></part></template>
[[Image:Space shuttle enterprise star trek.jpg|thumb|235px|[[Prototype]] [[Space Shuttle Enterprise|space shuttle ''Enterprise'']] named after the [[USS Enterprise (NCC-1701)|fictional starship]] with ''Star Trek'' television cast members and creator Gene Roddenberry.]]
The ''Star Trek'' media franchise is a multi-billion dollar industry, currently owned by CBS.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;billion&quot;</attr><inner>[http://www.startrek.com/startrek/view/features/specials/article/2674.html STARTREK.COM : Article] URL accessed August 24, 2006</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> Gene Roddenberry sold ''Star Trek'' to [[NBC]] as a classic adventure drama; he pitched the show as &quot;''Wagon Train'' to the Stars&quot; and as [[Horatio Hornblower]] in Space.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;analogies&quot;</attr><inner>[http://www.centennialofflight.gov/essay/Social/star_trek/SH7.htm Social History :Star Trek as a Cultural Phenomenon] URL accesses August 24, 2006</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> The opening line, &quot;to boldly go where no man has gone before,&quot; was taken almost verbatim from a [[United States|US]] [[White House]] booklet on space produced after the ''[[Sputnik]]'' flight in 1957.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Whiet House&quot;</attr><inner>[http://www.fas.org/spp/guide/usa/intro1958.html Introduction to Outer Space (1958)] URL accessed August 24, 2006</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> The central trio of Kirk, Spock, and [[Leonard McCoy|McCoy]] was modeled on [[classical mythology|classical mythological]] storytelling.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;analogies&quot;</attr></ext>

''Star Trek'' and its spin-offs have proved highly popular in television repeats and are currently shown on TV stations worldwide.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;worldwide&quot;</attr><inner>[http://eugene.roddenberry.com/treknationproposal.rtf TREK NATION] [[Rich Text Format|RTF]] URL accessed August 24, 2006</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> The show’s cultural impact goes far beyond its longevity and profitability. ''Star Trek'' [[science fiction convention|conventions]] have become popular, though they're often merged now with conventions related to other genres and series. Some fans have coined the term [[Trekkie|''Trekkies'']] to describe themselves. Others, however, prefer the term ''Trekkers.'' Fans of ''Deep Space Nine'' are better known as ''Niners.'' An entire subculture has grown up around the show<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Trekkies&quot;</attr><inner>[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0120370/ Trekkies (1997)] URL accessed August 24, 2006</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> which was documented in the film ''[[Trekkies (film)|Trekkies]]''. ''Star Trek'' was the top rank cult show by [[TV guide]].<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;top cult&quot;</attr><inner>{{cite web |url=http://www.tvguide.com/news/top-cult-shows-40239.aspx |title=TV Guide Names the Top Cult Shows Ever |publisher=''[[TV Guide]]'' |date=2007-06-29 |accessdate=2008-11-25}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

The ''Star Trek'' franchise has influenced the design of many current technologies, including the [[Tablet PC]], the [[Personal digital assistant|PDA]], [[mobile phones]], and the [[MRI]] (based on Dr. McCoy's diagnostic table).<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;modern&quot;</attr><inner>[http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2004/03/15/BUGO35EG1T83.DTL 40 years since the Enterprise's inception, some of its science fiction gadgets are part of everyday life] URL accessed August 24, 2006</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> It has also brought to popular attention the concept of [[teleportation]] with its depiction of &quot;matter-energy transport.&quot; Phrases such as &quot;[[Beam me up, Scotty]]&quot; have entered the public vernacular.<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Scotty&quot;</attr><inner>[http://www.worldwidewords.org/articles/startrek.htm Articles: Beam me up, Scotty!] URL accessed August 24, 2006</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> In 1976, following a letter-writing campaign, [[NASA]] named its prototype [[Space Shuttle program|space shuttle]] [[Space Shuttle Enterprise|''Enterprise'']], after the [[Starship Enterprise|fictional starship]].<ext><name>ref</name><attr> name=&quot;Enterprise&quot;</attr><inner>[http://science.ksc.nasa.gov/shuttle/resources/orbiters/enterprise.html Shuttle Orbiter Enterprise (OV-101)] URL accessed August 24, 2006</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

Beyond Star Trek's technological innovations, one of its greatest and most significant contributions to TV history is its creation of a cast different races and cultures in the sets. This became common in television shows in the 1980s such as ''[[L.A. Law]]'' but was controversial and daring in the 1960s. On the bridge of the Enterprise was a Japanese helmsman, a Russian navigator, a female African-American communications officer, and a Vulcan-Earthling first officer - among other members. Also, controversial at its time (in the episode ''[[Plato's Stepchildren]]''), was Captain Kirk's kiss with Lt. Uhura which became a defining moment in television history as it was American TV's first interracial kiss.

<h level="3" i="21">===Parodies===</h>
Notable parodies of ''Star Trek'' include the ''[[Star Wreck]]'' movie series, the internet-based cartoon series ''[[Stone Trek]]'', the ''[[Star Wreck (novel series)|Star Wreck]]'' novel series, the song ''[[Star Trekkin']]'' by [[The Firm (Star Trekkin')|The Firm]], the feature film ''[[Galaxy Quest]]'', an episode of ''[[Futurama]]'' called &quot;[[Where No Fan Has Gone Before]]&quot; which featured several characters from the original series, and the episode of ''[[Family Guy]]'' titled &quot;[[Not All Dogs Go to Heaven]]&quot;, which featured the entire cast of ''[[Star Trek The Next Generation]]'', as well as an episode of ''[[The Simpsons]]'' titled &quot;[[Itchy &amp; Scratchy: The Movie]]&quot;, featuring some of the cast of the original ''Star Trek'' television series.  The [[news satire]] site [[The Onion]] created a ''Star Trek XI'' based clip just before the release of the film.

<h level="2" i="22">==Awards and honors==</h>
Of the various science-fiction awards given for drama, only the [[Hugo award]] dates back as far as the original series. Although the Hugo is mainly given for print-media science-fiction, its &quot;best drama&quot; award is usually given to film or television presentations. The Hugo does ''not'' give out awards for best actor, director, or other aspects of film production. Prior to 2002, films and television shows competed for the same Hugo, before the split of the drama award into short drama and long drama. In 1968, all five nominees for a Hugo award were individual episodes of ''Star Trek'', as were three of the five nominees in 1967 (the other two being the films ''Fahrenheit 451'' and ''Fantastic Voyage''). The only ''Star Trek'' series to ''not'' get even a Hugo ''nomination'' are the animated series and ''Voyager'', though only the original series and ''Next Generation'' ever actually won the award. No ''Star Trek'' film has ever won a Hugo, though a few were nominated. In 2008, the fan made episode of [[Star Trek: New Voyages]] entitled 'World Enough and Time' was nominated for the Hugo for best short drama, where it competed with professional episodes from shows such as [[Doctor Who]] and [[Battlestar Galactica]].<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>Full lists of Hugo award winners are at [http://dpsinfo.com/awardweb/hugos] Nominations can be found at [http://www.locusmag.com/SFAwards/Db/HugoNomList.html]</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

The prestigious science-fiction [[Saturn awards|Saturn award]] did not exist during broadcasting of the original series. Unlike the Hugo, the Saturn award ''does'' give out prizes for best actor, special effects, music, etc. Also unlike the Hugo (until 2002) movies and television shows have never competed against each other for Saturns. The two ''Star Trek'' series to win multiple Saturn awards during their run were ''The Next Generation'' (twice winning for best television series) and ''Voyager'' (twice winning for best actress- [[Kate Mulgrew]] and [[Jeri Ryan]]). The original series retroactively won a Saturn award for best DVD release. Several ''Star Trek'' films have won Saturns including categories such as best actor, actress, director, costume design, and special effects. However, ''Star Trek'' has never won a Saturn for best make-up.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>[http://www.locusmag.com/SFAwards/Db/SaturnNomList.html Saturn award winners and nominees can be found at]</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

The Star Trek series has also won 31 Emmy Awards.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>[http://www.emmys.com/award_history_search?page=2&amp;person=&amp;program=star%20trek&amp;start_year=1989&amp;end_year=2009&amp;network=All&amp;web_category=All&amp;winner=Y Emmy Awards for the Star Trek Series]</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

<h level="2" i="23">== See also ==</h>
<template lineStart="1"><title>portal</title></template>

<h level="2" i="24">==Notes==</h>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Reflist</title><part><name index="1"/><value>3</value></part></template>

<h level="2" i="25">==References==</h>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Refbegin</title></template>
*<template><title>Cite book </title><part><name> last</name><equals>=</equals><value>Asherman </value></part><part><name> first</name><equals>=</equals><value>Allan </value></part><part><name> title</name><equals>=</equals><value>The Star Trek Compendium </value></part><part><name> location</name><equals>=</equals><value>New York </value></part><part><name> publisher</name><equals>=</equals><value>Simon &amp; Schuster </value></part><part><name> year</name><equals>=</equals><value>1981 </value></part><part><name> isbn</name><equals>=</equals><value>0671791451</value></part></template>
*<template><title>Cite book </title><part><name>last</name><equals>=</equals><value>Barad, Ph. D. </value></part><part><name>first</name><equals>=</equals><value>Judith </value></part><part><name>coauthors</name><equals>=</equals><value>Robertson, Ed </value></part><part><name>year</name><equals>=</equals><value>2000 </value></part><part><name>title</name><equals>=</equals><value>The Ethics of Star Trek </value></part><part><name>location</name><equals>=</equals><value> </value></part><part><name>publisher</name><equals>=</equals><value>HarperCollins </value></part><part><name>isbn</name><equals>=</equals><value>0060195304</value></part></template>
*<template><title>Cite book </title><part><name>last</name><equals>=</equals><value>Edited By </value></part><part><name>editor</name><equals>=</equals><value>Harrison, Taylor; Projansky, Sarah; Ono, Kent A.; Helford, Elyce Rae </value></part><part><name>year</name><equals>=</equals><value>1996 </value></part><part><name>title</name><equals>=</equals><value>Enterprise Zones: Critical Positions on Star Trek </value></part><part><name>location</name><equals>=</equals><value>Boulder </value></part><part><name>publisher</name><equals>=</equals><value>Westview Press </value></part><part><name>isbn</name><equals>=</equals><value>0813328993</value></part></template>
*<template><title>Cite book </title><part><name>last</name><equals>=</equals><value>Ellison </value></part><part><name>first</name><equals>=</equals><value>Harlan </value></part><part><name>year</name><equals>=</equals><value>1996 </value></part><part><name>title</name><equals>=</equals><value>City on the Edge of Forever </value></part><part><name>location</name><equals>=</equals><value> </value></part><part><name>publisher</name><equals>=</equals><value>Borderlands Press </value></part><part><name>isbn</name><equals>=</equals><value>1880325020</value></part></template>
*<template><title>Cite book </title><part><name>last</name><equals>=</equals><value>Gerrold </value></part><part><name>first</name><equals>=</equals><value>David </value></part><part><name>authorlink</name><equals>=</equals><value>David Gerrold </value></part><part><name>year</name><equals>=</equals><value>1973 </value></part><part><name>title</name><equals>=</equals><value>The Trouble with Tribbles </value></part><part><name>location</name><equals>=</equals><value>New York </value></part><part><name>publisher</name><equals>=</equals><value>Ballantine </value></part><part><name>isbn</name><equals>=</equals><value>0345234022</value></part></template>
*<template><title>Cite book </title><part><name>last</name><equals>=</equals><value>Gerrold </value></part><part><name>first</name><equals>=</equals><value>David </value></part><part><name>year</name><equals>=</equals><value>1984 </value></part><part><name>title</name><equals>=</equals><value>The World of Star Trek—Revised Edition</value></part><part><name>origyear</name><equals>=</equals><value>1973</value></part><part><name>publisher</name><equals>=</equals><value>Ballantine Books </value></part><part><name>edition</name><equals>=</equals><value>Bluejay Books </value></part><part><name>id</name><equals>=</equals><value><template><title>ASIN</title><part><name index="1"/><value>B000JWHTXU</value></part></template> </value></part></template>
*<template><title>Cite book </title><part><name>last</name><equals>=</equals><value>Greenwald </value></part><part><name>first</name><equals>=</equals><value>Jeff </value></part><part><name>year</name><equals>=</equals><value>1998 </value></part><part><name>title</name><equals>=</equals><value>Future Perfect: How Star Trek Conquered Planet Earth </value></part><part><name>location</name><equals>=</equals><value> </value></part><part><name>publisher</name><equals>=</equals><value>Viking Press </value></part><part><name>isbn</name><equals>=</equals><value>0670873993</value></part></template>
*<template><title>cite book</title><part><name>last</name><equals>=</equals><value>Johnson-Smith</value></part><part><name>first</name><equals>=</equals><value>Jan </value></part><part><name>title</name><equals>=</equals><value>American Science Fiction TV: Star Trek, Stargate and Beyond</value></part><part><name>publisher</name><equals>=</equals><value>I B Tauris &amp; Co Ltd</value></part><part><name>year</name><equals>=</equals><value> 2005</value></part><part><name>isbn</name><equals>=</equals><value> 1860648827</value></part></template>
*<template><title>Cite book </title><part><name>last</name><equals>=</equals><value>Krauss </value></part><part><name>first</name><equals>=</equals><value>Lawrence M </value></part><part><name>year</name><equals>=</equals><value>1995 </value></part><part><name>title</name><equals>=</equals><value>The Physics of Star Trek </value></part><part><name>location</name><equals>=</equals><value> </value></part><part><name>publisher</name><equals>=</equals><value>Basic Books </value></part><part><name>isbn</name><equals>=</equals><value>0465005594</value></part></template>
*<template><title>Cite book </title><part><name>last</name><equals>=</equals><value>Lake </value></part><part><name>first</name><equals>=</equals><value>M.N. </value></part><part><name>year</name><equals>=</equals><value>2005 </value></part><part><name>title</name><equals>=</equals><value>Picard: The Academy Years </value></part><part><name>location</name><equals>=</equals><value> </value></part><part><name>publisher</name><equals>=</equals><value>Dragon Publishing </value></part><part><name>isbn</name><equals>=</equals><value/></part></template>
*<template><title>Cite book </title><part><name>last</name><equals>=</equals><value>Lichtenberg </value></part><part><name>first</name><equals>=</equals><value>Jacqueline </value></part><part><name>coauthors</name><equals>=</equals><value>Marshak, Sondra; [[Joan Winston|Winston, Joan]] </value></part><part><name>year</name><equals>=</equals><value>1975 </value></part><part><name>title</name><equals>=</equals><value>Star Trek Lives! </value></part><part><name>location</name><equals>=</equals><value>Toronto </value></part><part><name>publisher</name><equals>=</equals><value>Bantam Books </value></part><part><name>isbn</name><equals>=</equals><value>0552099147</value></part></template>
*<template><title>Cite book </title><part><name>last</name><equals>=</equals><value>McIntee </value></part><part><name>forst</name><equals>=</equals><value>David </value></part><part><name>year</name><equals>=</equals><value>2000 </value></part><part><name>title</name><equals>=</equals><value>Delta Quadrant—The Unofficial Guide to Star Trek Voyager </value></part><part><name>location</name><equals>=</equals><value> London</value></part><part><name>publisher</name><equals>=</equals><value> Virgin</value></part><part><name>isbn</name><equals>=</equals><value>0753504367</value></part></template>
*<template><title>Cite book </title><part><name>last</name><equals>=</equals><value>Nichols </value></part><part><name>first</name><equals>=</equals><value>Nichelle </value></part><part><name>year</name><equals>=</equals><value>1994 </value></part><part><name>title</name><equals>=</equals><value>Beyond Uhura </value></part><part><name>location</name><equals>=</equals><value> </value></part><part><name>publisher</name><equals>=</equals><value>Putnam </value></part><part><name>isbn</name><equals>=</equals><value>0679435093</value></part></template>
*<template><title>Cite book </title><part><name>last</name><equals>=</equals><value>Sackett </value></part><part><name>first</name><equals>=</equals><value>Susan </value></part><part><name>authorlink</name><equals>=</equals><value>Susan Sackett </value></part><part><name>year</name><equals>=</equals><value>2002 </value></part><part><name>title</name><equals>=</equals><value>Inside Trek: My Secret Life with Star Trek Creator Gene Roddenberry </value></part><part><name>location</name><equals>=</equals><value> </value></part><part><name>publisher</name><equals>=</equals><value>Hawk Publishing Group </value></part><part><name>isbn</name><equals>=</equals><value>1930709420</value></part></template>
*<template><title>Cite book </title><part><name>last1</name><equals>=</equals><value>Shatner </value></part><part><name>first1</name><equals>=</equals><value>William </value></part><part><name>authorlink1</name><equals>=</equals><value>William Shatner</value></part><part><name>last2</name><equals>=</equals><value>Kreski</value></part><part><name>first2</name><equals>=</equals><value>Chris</value></part><part><name>authorlink2</name><equals>=</equals><value>Chris Kreski </value></part><part><name>year</name><equals>=</equals><value>1993 </value></part><part><name>title</name><equals>=</equals><value>Star Trek Memories </value></part><part><name>location</name><equals>=</equals><value> </value></part><part><name>publisher</name><equals>=</equals><value>HarperCollins </value></part><part><name>isbn</name><equals>=</equals><value>0060177349</value></part></template>
*<template><title>Cite book </title><part><name>last</name><equals>=</equals><value>Shatner </value></part><part><name>first</name><equals>=</equals><value>William </value></part><part><name>coauthors</name><equals>=</equals><value>Kreski, Chris </value></part><part><name>year</name><equals>=</equals><value>1994 </value></part><part><name>title</name><equals>=</equals><value>Star Trek Movie Memories </value></part><part><name>location</name><equals>=</equals><value> </value></part><part><name>publisher</name><equals>=</equals><value>HarperCollins </value></part><part><name>isbn</name><equals>=</equals><value>0060176172</value></part></template>
*<template><title>Cite book </title><part><name>last</name><equals>=</equals><value>Shatner </value></part><part><name>first</name><equals>=</equals><value>William </value></part><part><name>coauthors</name><equals>=</equals><value>Kreski, Chris </value></part><part><name>year</name><equals>=</equals><value>1999 </value></part><part><name>title</name><equals>=</equals><value>Get a Life! </value></part><part><name>location</name><equals>=</equals><value>New York </value></part><part><name>publisher</name><equals>=</equals><value>Pocket Books </value></part><part><name>isbn</name><equals>=</equals><value>0671021311</value></part></template>
*<template><title>Cite book </title><part><name>last</name><equals>=</equals><value>Shatner </value></part><part><name>first</name><equals>=</equals><value>William </value></part><part><name>coauthors</name><equals>=</equals><value>Walter, Chip </value></part><part><name>year</name><equals>=</equals><value>2002 </value></part><part><name>title</name><equals>=</equals><value>I'm Working on That: A Trek from Science Fiction to Science Fact </value></part><part><name>location</name><equals>=</equals><value>New York </value></part><part><name>publisher</name><equals>=</equals><value>Pocket Books </value></part><part><name>isbn</name><equals>=</equals><value>067104737X</value></part></template>
*<template><title>Cite book </title><part><name>last</name><equals>=</equals><value>Solow </value></part><part><name>first</name><equals>=</equals><value>Herbert F. </value></part><part><name>coauthors</name><equals>=</equals><value>Justman, Robert H. </value></part><part><name>year</name><equals>=</equals><value>1996 </value></part><part><name>title</name><equals>=</equals><value>Inside Star Trek: The Real Story </value></part><part><name>location</name><equals>=</equals><value>New York </value></part><part><name>publisher</name><equals>=</equals><value>Pocket Books </value></part><part><name>isbn</name><equals>=</equals><value>0671896288</value></part></template>
*<template><title>Cite book </title><part><name>last</name><equals>=</equals><value>Trimble </value></part><part><name>first</name><equals>=</equals><value>Bjo </value></part><part><name>authorlink</name><equals>=</equals><value>Bjo Trimble</value></part><part><name>year</name><equals>=</equals><value>1983 </value></part><part><name>title</name><equals>=</equals><value>On the Good Ship Enterprise: My 15 Years with Star Trek </value></part><part><name>location</name><equals>=</equals><value> </value></part><part><name>publisher</name><equals>=</equals><value>Donning Starblaze </value></part><part><name>isbn</name><equals>=</equals><value>0898652537</value></part></template>
*<template><title>Cite book </title><part><name>last</name><equals>=</equals><value>Turnbull </value></part><part><name>first</name><equals>=</equals><value>Gerry </value></part><part><name>year</name><equals>=</equals><value>1979 </value></part><part><name>title</name><equals>=</equals><value>A Star Trek Catalog </value></part><part><name>location</name><equals>=</equals><value> </value></part><part><name>publisher</name><equals>=</equals><value>Grosset &amp; Dunlap </value></part><part><name>isbn</name><equals>=</equals><value>0441784771</value></part></template>
*<template><title>Cite book </title><part><name>last</name><equals>=</equals><value>Whitfield</value></part><part><name>first</name><equals>=</equals><value>Stephen PE </value></part><part><name>coauthors</name><equals>=</equals><value>Roddenberry, Gene </value></part><part><name>year</name><equals>=</equals><value>1968 </value></part><part><name>title</name><equals>=</equals><value>The Making of Star Trek</value></part><part><name>location</name><equals>=</equals><value>New York </value></part><part><name>publisher</name><equals>=</equals><value>Ballantine Books </value></part><part><name>oclc</name><equals>=</equals><value>23859</value></part></template>
*<template><title>Cite book </title><part><name>last</name><equals>=</equals><value>Winston </value></part><part><name>first</name><equals>=</equals><value>Joan </value></part><part><name>authorlink</name><equals>=</equals><value>Joan Winston </value></part><part><name>year</name><equals>=</equals><value>1977 </value></part><part><name>title</name><equals>=</equals><value>The Making of the Trek Conventions </value></part><part><name>location</name><equals>=</equals><value>Garden City, NY </value></part><part><name>publisher</name><equals>=</equals><value>Doubleday Books/Playboy Press </value></part><part><name>isbn</name><equals>=</equals><value>0385131127</value></part></template>

<h level="2" i="26">==External links==</h>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Commons category</title><part><name index="1"/><value>Star Trek</value></part></template>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Wikiquote</title></template>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Wiktionary</title></template>
<comment>&lt;!-- NOTE: NO RANDOM FAN SITES; ONLY ADD LINKS IF THEY ARE GENUINELY INFORMATIVE; OTHERWISE THEY ARE LIKELY TO BE REMOVED --&gt;
</comment>*[http://www.startrek.com StarTrek.com]—The Official ''Star Trek'' website	
*[http://www.memory-alpha.org/en/index.php/Main_Page Memory Alpha]—A ''Star Trek'' encyclopedia that uses information ''only'' from canon sources licensed by Paramount.	
*[http://startrek.wikia.com Memory Beta]—A ''Star Trek'' encyclopedia that uses information from ''both'' canon and non-canon sources licensed by Paramount.	
*[http://www.cbs.com/classics/star_trek/video/video.php CBS Video]—Free full-length ''Star Trek: The Original Series'' episodes provided by CBS (only available in the United States)

<template lineStart="1"><title>Star Trek</title></template>

[[Category:Star Trek| ]]
[[Category:American science fiction television series]]
[[Category:Film series]]
[[Category:Media franchises]]
[[Category:Television franchises]]

<template lineStart="1"><title>Link FA</title><part><name index="1"/><value>it</value></part></template>
<template lineStart="1"><title>Link FA</title><part><name index="1"/><value>nl</value></part></template>
[[ar:ستار تريك]]
[[ast:Star Trek]]
[[bg:Стар Трек (вселена)]]
[[bn:স্টার ট্রেক]]
[[br:Star Trek]]
[[bs:Zvjezdane staze]]
[[ca:Star Trek]]
[[cs:Star Trek]]
[[cy:Star Trek]]
[[da:Star Trek]]
[[de:Star Trek]]
[[el:Σταρ Τρεκ]]
[[eo:Star Trek]]
[[es:Star Trek]]
[[et:Star Trek]]
[[fa:پیشتازان فضا]]
[[fi:Star Trek]]
[[fr:Star Trek]]
[[ga:Star Trek]]
[[gl:Star Trek]]
[[he:מסע בין כוכבים]]
[[hr:Zvjezdane staze]]
[[hu:Star Trek]]
[[id:Star Trek]]
[[is:Star Trek]]
[[it:Star Trek]]
[[ja:スタートレック]]
[[ko:스타트렉]]
[[la:Iter Stellare]]
[[lb:Star Trek]]
[[li:Star Trek]]
[[lv:Zvaigžņu ceļš]]
[[mk:Ѕвездени патеки]]
[[mr:स्टार ट्रेक]]
[[ms:Star Trek]]
[[nds:Star Trek]]
[[nl:Star Trek]]
[[nn:Star Trek]]
[[no:Star Trek]]
[[pl:Star Trek]]
[[pt:Star Trek]]
[[ro:Star Trek]]
[[ru:Звёздный путь]]
[[sh:Zvjezdane staze]]
[[simple:Star Trek]]
[[sk:Star Trek (filmy a seriály)]]
[[sl:Zvezdne steze]]
[[sq:Udhëtimi yjor]]
[[sr:Звездане стазе]]
[[st:Star Trek]]
[[sv:Star Trek]]
[[th:สตาร์ เทรค]]
[[tl:Star Trek]]
[[tr:Uzay Yolu]]
[[uk:Зоряний шлях]]
[[zh:星艦奇航記]]
[[zh-min-nan:Star Trek]]</root>