<root>'''Shortened spoken version:'''

You're listenig to a shortended version of the article '''Oktoberfest''', from Wikipedia, the free encyclopedia, at E N dot wikipedia dot org.

'''Oktoberfest''' is the world's largest [[fair]] held annually in [[Munich]], [[Bavaria]], [[Germany]]. It is 16-day festival running from late September to the first weekend in October with more than 6 million people from around the world attending the event every year. To the locals, it is not called Oktoberfest, but &quot;die Wiesn&quot;, after the colloquial name of the fairgrounds ([[Theresienwiese]]) themselves. The Oktoberfest is an important part of [[Bavaria]]n culture, having been held since 1810. Other cities across the world also hold [[Oktoberfest celebrations]], modeled after the original Munich event.

The Munich Oktoberfest originally took place during the sixteen days up to, and including, the first Sunday in October. In 1994, the schedule was modified in response to [[German reunification]] so that if the first Sunday in October falls on the 1st or 2nd, then the festival would go on until October 3 ([[German Unity Day]]). Thus, the festival is now 17 days when the first Sunday is October 2 and 18 days when it is October 1. In 2010, the festival lasted until the first Monday in October, to mark the anniversary of the event. The festival is held in an area named the ''[[Theresienwiese]]'' (field, or [[meadow]], of [[Therese of Saxe-Hildburghausen|Therese]]), often called ''Wiesn'' for short, located near Munich's center. Large quantities of [[Oktoberfest Beer]] are consumed, with almost 7 million liters served during the 16 day festival in 2007.  Visitors may also enjoy a wide variety of traditional food such as [[Hendl]] ([[chicken]]), Schweinebraten ([[roast]] [[pork]]), [[Schweinshaxe]] (grilled [[ham hock]]), Steckerlfisch (grilled fish on a stick), Würstl ([[sausages]]) along with Brezeln ([[pretzel]]), [[Klöße|Knödel]] (potato or bread dumplings), [[Käsespätzle]] (cheese noodles), Reiberdatschi ([[potato pancakes]]), [[Sauerkraut]] or Rotkohl/Blaukraut ([[red cabbage]]) along with such Bavarian delicacies as [[Obatzda]] (a spiced cheese-butter spread) and [[Weisswurst]] (a white sausage).

<h level="2" i="1">== The Beers ==</h>
Only beer conforming to the [[Reinheitsgebot]], at a minimum of 13.5% [[Stammwürze]] (approximately 6% alcohol by volume) may be served at Oktoberfest. The beer must also be brewed within the city limits of Munich. Beers meeting these criteria may be designated [[Oktoberfest Beer]].
<template lineStart="1"><title>Citation needed</title><part><name>date</name><equals>=</equals><value>January 2012</value></part></template>

The breweries that can produce Oktoberfest Beer under the criteria are: <template><title>Citation needed</title><part><name>date</name><equals>=</equals><value>January 2012</value></part></template>
* [[Augustiner Bräu|Augustiner-Bräu]]
* [[Hacker-Pschorr|Hacker-Pschorr-Bräu]]
* [[Löwenbräu]]
* [[Paulaner|Paulaner-Bräu]]
* [[Spaten|Spatenbräu]]
* Staatliches [[Hofbräuhaus|Hofbräu-München]]

Oktoberfest Beer is a registered Trademark by the Club of Munich Brewers.

<h level="2" i="2">==History==</h>
Crown Prince Ludwig, later to become [[Ludwig I, King of Bavaria|King Ludwig I]], was married to Princess [[Therese of Saxe-Hildburghausen]] on October 17, 1810. The citizens of Munich were invited to attend the festivities held on the fields in front of the city gates to celebrate the happy royal event. The fields were named Theresienwiese (&quot;Theresa's meadow&quot;) in honor of the Crown Princess, and have kept that name ever since, although the locals have since abbreviated the name simply to the &quot;Wies'n&quot;.

[[Horse race]]s in the presence of the Royal Family marked the close of the event that was celebrated as a festival for the whole of Bavaria. The decision to repeat the horse races in the subsequent year gave rise to the tradition of the Oktoberfest.

&quot;The festival was eventually prolonged and moved ahead to September to allow for better weather conditions. Today, the last day of the festival is the first Sunday in October. In 2006, the Oktoberfest extended two extra days because the first Tuesday, October 3, was a national holiday. Over the past 200 years, Oktoberfest was canceled 24 times due to [[cholera]] epidemics and war.&quot;<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>http://www.vistawide.com/german/oktoberfest/oktoberfest.htm</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext>

<h level="3" i="3">===First hundred years===</h>
In 1811, an agricultural show was added to promote Bavarian [[agriculture]]. The [[horse race]] persisted until 1960, the agricultural show still exists and  is held every four years on the southern part of the festival grounds. In 1816, carnival booths appeared; the main prizes were [[silver]], [[porcelain]], and jewelry. The founding citizens of Munich assumed responsibility for festival management in 1819, and it was decided to make the Oktoberfest an annual event. Later, it was lengthened and the date pushed forward, because days are longer and warmer at the end of September.

To honour the marriage of [[Ludwig I, King of Bavaria|Prince Ludwig]] and [[Therese of Saxe-Hildburghausen]], a parade took place for the first time in 1810. Since 1850, this has become an annual event and an important component of the Oktoberfest. Eight thousand people—mostly from Bavaria—in traditional costumes walk from Maximilian Street through the centre of Munich to the Oktoberfest grounds. The march is led by the ''[[Münchner Kindl]]''.

Since 1850, the [[Bavaria statue|statue of Bavaria]] has watched the Oktoberfest. This worldly Bavarian [[patron]] was first sketched by [[Leo von Klenze]] in a classic style and [[Ludwig Michael Schwanthaler]] romanticised and &quot;[[germanisation|Germanised]]&quot; the draft. The statue was constructed by [[Johann Baptist Stiglmaier]] and [[Ferdinand von Miller]].

In 1853, the Bavarian [[Ruhmeshalle (Munich)|Ruhmeshalle]] was completed. In 1854, the festival was cancelled after 3,000 residents of Munich died during a [[cholera]] epidemic. There was no Oktoberfest in 1866 because Bavaria was involved in the [[Austro-Prussian War]]. In 1870, the [[Franco-Prussian War]] forced the cancellation of the festival. In 1873, the festival was cancelled due to another cholera epidemic. In 1880, the electric light illuminated more than 400 booths and tents. In 1881, booths selling [[bratwurst]] opened. Beer was first served in glass mugs in 1892.

At the end of the 19th century, a re-organization took place. Until then, there were games of [[Skittles (sport)|skittles]], large dance floors, and trees for climbing in the beer booths. Organizers wanted more room for guests and musicians. The booths became beer halls.

In 1887, the Entry of the Oktoberfest Staff and Breweries took place for the first time. This event showcases the splendidly decorated horse teams of the breweries and the bands that play in the festival tents. This event always takes place on the first Saturday of the Oktoberfest and serves as the official prelude to the Oktoberfest celebration

In 1910, Oktoberfest celebrated its 100th anniversary. Some 120,000 litres of beer were poured. In 1913, the Bräurosl was founded, which was the largest Oktoberfest beer tent ever, with room for ~ 12,000 people.

<h level="3" i="4">===War years===</h>
From 1914 to 1918, [[World War I]] prevented the celebration of Oktoberfest. In 1919 and 1920, the two years after the war, Munich celebrated only an &quot;Autumn Fest.&quot; In 1923 and 1924, the Oktoberfest was not held due to [[Hyperinflation in the Weimar Republic|inflation]].

In 1933, the Bavarian white and blue flag was replaced with the [[Flag of Nazi Germany|swastika flag]]. During [[World War II]], from 1939 to 1945, no Oktoberfest took place. Following the war, from 1946 to 1948, Munich celebrated only the &quot;Autumn Fest.&quot;

<h level="3" i="5">===Modern festival===</h>
Since 1950, there has been a traditional festival opening: A twelve gun salute and the tapping of the first keg of Oktoberfest beer at 12:00 by the incumbent Mayor of Munich with the cry &quot;''Ozapft is!''&quot; (&quot;It's tapped!&quot; in the [[Austro-Bavarian language|Austro-Bavarian dialect]]). The Mayor then gives the first beer to the [[List of Ministers-President of Bavaria|Minister-President of the State of Bavaria]]. The first mayor to tap the keg was [[Thomas Wimmer]].

Horse races ended in 1960.

By 1960, the Oktoberfest had turned into an enormous world-famous festival. Since then, foreigners began to picture Germans as wearing the [[Sennerhut]], [[Lederhosen]], and the girls in [[Dirndl]].

Traditional visitors wear during the Oktoberfest Bavarian hats (''Tirolerhüte''), which contain a tuft of goat hair. In Germany, goat hair is highly valued and prized, making it one of the most expensive objects for sale. The more tufts of goat hair on your hat, the wealthier you are considered to be. Technology helping, this tradition ended with the appearance of cheap goat hair imitations on the market.

There are many problems every year with young people who overestimate their ability to handle large amounts of alcohol. Many forget that Oktoberfest beer has 5.8 to 6.3% alcohol and high sugar content (compared to an average of 5.2% of alcohol and low sugar content in German beer), and they pass out due to intoxication. These drunk patrons are often called &quot;Bierleichen&quot; (German for &quot;beer corpses&quot;).

Since the 1970s, local German gay organizations have organized &quot;Gay Days&quot; at Oktoberfest, which by the 21st century always began in the Bräurosl tent on the first Sunday.

To keep the Oktoberfest, and especially the beer tents, friendly for older people and families, the concept of the &quot;quiet Oktoberfest&quot; was developed in 2005. Until 6:00&amp;nbsp;pm, the tents only play quiet music, for example traditional wind music. Only after that will [[Schlager]] and pop music be played, which had led to more violence in earlier years.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite web
|url=http://www.houblon.net/spip.php?article2482
|title=Rules for Oktoberfest jeered |publisher=www.houblon.net |accessdate=2008-09-20 |last= |first=}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> The music played in the afternoon is limited to 85 [[decibels]]. With these rules, the organisers of the Oktoberfest were able to curb the over-the-top party mentality and preserve the traditional beer tent atmosphere.

Since 2005 the last travelling Enterprise ride of Germany, called Mondlift, is back on the Oktoberfest.

Starting in 2008, a new Bavarian law intended to ban smoking in all enclosed spaces that are open to the public, even at the Oktoberfest. Because of problems enforcing the anti-smoking law in the big tents there was an exception for the Oktoberfest 2008, although the sale of tobacco was not allowed. After heavy losses in the 2008 local elections with the smoke ban being a big issue in debates, the state's ruling party meanwhile implemented special exemptions to beer tents and small pubs. The change in regulation is aimed in particular at large tents at the Oktoberfest:<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite journal |url=http://www.spiegel.de/international/germany/0,1518,539902,00.html |title=Up in Smoke: Bavarian Politicians Want to Relax Smoking Ban |journal=Spiegel Online International |date=03/06/2008 |accessdate=28 November 2010 }}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> So, smoking in the tents is still legal, but the tents usually have non-smoking areas.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite web |url=http://www.oktoberfest.de/en/article/About+the+Oktoberfest/About+the+Oktoberfest/Smoking+at+the+Oktoberfest/823/ |title=Smoking at the Oktoberfest |publisher=oktoberfest.de |accessdate=28 November 2010}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> The sale of tobacco in the tents is now legal, but it is abandoned by agreement. However, in early 2010 a referendum held in Bavaria as a result of a popular initiative re-instituted the original, strict, smoking ban of 2008; thus, no beer will be sold to people caught smoking in the tents.<ext><name>ref</name><attr/><inner>{{cite journal |url=http://www.spiegel.de/reise/aktuell/0,1518,709179,00.html |title=Oktoberfest 2010 – Raucher sollen kein Bier kriegen |date=29 July 2010|journal=Spiegel Online |accessdate=28 November 2010 |language=German}}</inner><close>&lt;/ref&gt;</close></ext> The blanket smoking ban will not take effect until 2011.

2010 marks the 200th anniversary of Oktoberfest. For the anniversary, there was a horse race in historical costumes on opening day. A so-called &quot;Historische Wiesn&quot; (historical Oktoberfest) took place, starting one day earlier than usual on the southern part of the festival grounds. A specially brewed beer (solely available at the tents of the historical Oktoberfest), horse races, and a museum tent gave visitors an impression of how the event felt a century ago.

<h level="3" i="6">===1980 Oktoberfest bomb blast===</h>
A [[pipe bomb]] was set off in a dustbin at the restrooms at the main entrance on September 26, 1980. The bomb consisted of an empty [[fire extinguisher]] filled with 1.39 kilograms of [[trinitrotoluene|TNT]] and mortar shells. Thirteen people were killed, over 201 were injured, 68 seriously. This was the second deadliest terrorist attack in the history of Germany after the [[Munich Massacre]]. Governmental authorities propounded a summary of official inquires, purporting that a [[Far right|right-wing extremist]] [[Gundolf Köhler]] from [[Donaueschingen]], a social outcast who was killed in the explosion, was the lone perpetrator. However, this account is [[Operation Gladio#The 1980 Oktoberfest bomb blast|strongly disputed]] by various groups.


You were listening to a shortened version of the article Oktoberfest spoken on the 29th of September in 2013 by the User LordOider. The article can be found under E N dot wikipedia dot org slash wiki slash Oktoberfest, a version history with all authors of the text can be found there under the link View history. This sound file and all text in the article are licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License, available at creativecommons dot org.</root>